Cantata-140

by Philip K. Dick

The young couple, black-haired, dark-skinned, probably Mexican or Puerto Rican, stood nervously at Herb Lackmore’s counter and the boy, the husband, said in a low voice, “Sir, we want to be put to sleep. We want to become bibs.”

Rising from his desk, Lackmore walked to the counter and although he did not like Cols—there seemed to be more of them every month, coming into his Oakland branch office of the U.S.

Department on Special Public Welfare—he said in a pleasant tone of voice designed to reassure the two of them, “Have you thought it over carefully, folks? It’s a big step. You might be out for, say, a few hundred years. Have you shopped for any professional advice about this?”

The boy, glancing at his wife, swallowed and murmured, “No, sir. We just decided between us. Neither of us can get a job and we’re about to be evicted from our dorm. We don’t even own a wheel, and what can you do without a wheel? You can’t go anywhere. You can’t even look for work.” He was not a bad-looking boy, Lackmore noticed. Possibly eighteen, he still wore the coat and trousers which were army-separation issue. The girl had long hair; she was quite small, with black, bright eyes and a delicately-formed almost doll-like face. She never ceased watching her husband.

“I’m going to have a baby,” the girl blurted.

“Aw, the heck with both of you,” Lackmore said in disgust, drawing his breath in sharply. “You both get right out of here.”

Ducking their heads guiltily the boy and his wife turned and started from Lackmore’s office, back outside onto the busy downtown early-morning Oakland, California street.

“Go see an abort-consultant!” Lackmore called after them irritably. He resented having to help them, but obviously someone had to; look at the spot they had gotten themselves into. Because no doubt they were living on a government military pension, and if the girl was pregnant the pension would automatically be withdrawn.

Plucking hesitantly at the sleeve of his wrinkled coat the Col boy said, “Sir, how do we find an abort-consultant?”

The ignorance of the dark-skinned strata, despite the government’s ceaseless educational campaigns. No wonder their women were often preg. “Look in the phone book,” Lackmore said.

“Under abortionists, therapeutic. Then the subsection advisors. Got it?”

“Yes, sir. Thank you.” The boy nodded rapidly.

“Can you read?”

“Yes. I stayed in school until I was thirteen.” On the boy’s face fierce pride showed; his black eyes gleamed.

Lackmore returned to reading his homeopape; he did not have any more time to offer gratis. No wonder they wanted to become bibs. Preserved, unchanged, in a government warehouse, year after year, until—would the labor market ever improve? Lackmore personally doubted it, and he had been around a long time; he was ninety-five years old, a jerry. In his time he had put to sleep thousands of people, almost all of them, like this couple, young. And—dark.

The door of the office shut. The young couple had gone again as quietly as they had come.

Sighing, Lackmore began to read once more the pape’s article on the divorce trial of Lurton D.

Sands, Jr, the most sensational event now taking place; as always, he read every word of it avidly.

This day began for Darius Pethel with vidphone calls from irate customers wanting to know why their Jiffi−scuttlers hadn’t been fixed. Any time now, he told them soothingly, and hoped that Erickson was already at work in the service department of Pethel Jiffi−scuttler Sales & Service.

As soon as he was off the vidphone Pethel searched among the litter on his desk for the day’s copy of U.S. Business Report; he of course kept abreast of all the economic developments on the planet. This alone set him above his employees; this, his wealth, and his advanced age.

“What’s it say?” his salesman, Stu Hadley, asked, standing in the office doorway, robant magnetic broom in hand, pausing in his activity.

Silently, Pethel read the major headline.

EFFECTS ON THE NATION’S BUSINESS

COMMUNITY OF A NEGRO PRESIDENT

And there, in 3−D, animated, was a pic of James Briskin; the pic came to life, Candidate Briskin smiled in miniature, as Pethel pressed the tab beneath it. The Negro’s mustache-obscured lips moved and above his head a balloon appeared, filled with the words he was saying.

My first task will be to find an equitable disposition of the tens of millions of sleeping.

“And dump every last bib back on the labor market,” Pethel murmured, releasing the word tab. “If this guy gets in, the nation’s ruined.” But it was inevitable. Sooner or later, there would be a Negro president; after all, since the Event of 1993 there had been more Cols than Caucs.

Gloomily, he turned to page two for the latest on the Lurton Sands scandal; maybe that would cheer him up, the political news being so bad. The famous org-trans surgeon had become involved in a sensational contested divorce suit with his equally famous wife Myra, the abortconsultant. All sorts of juicy details were beginning to filter out, charges on both sides. Dr. Sands, according to the homeopapes, had a mistress; that was why Myra had stomped out, and rightly so. Not like the old days, Pethel thought, recalling his youth in the late decades of the twentieth century. Now it was 2080 and public—and private—morality had worsened.

Why would Dr. Sands want a mistress anyhow, Pethel wondered, when there’s that Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite passing overhead every day? They say there’re five thousand girls to choose from.

He, himself, had never visited Thisbe Olt’s satellite; he did not approve of it, nor did very many jerries—it was too radical a solution to the overpopulation problem, and seniors, by letter and telegram, had fought its passage in Congress back in ’72. But the bill had gone through anyhow . . . probably, he reflected, because most Congressmen had the idea of taking a jet’ab up there themselves. And no doubt regularly did, now.

“If we whites stick together—” Hadley began.

“Listen,” Pethel said, “that time has passed. If Briskin can dispose of the bibs, more power to him; personally, it keeps me awake at night, thinking of all those people, most of them just kids, lying in those gov warehouses year after year. Look at the talent going to waste. It’s—bureaucratic! Only a swollen socialist government would have dreamed up a solution like that.” He eyed his salesman harshly. “If you hadn’t gotten this job with me, even you might—”

Hadley interrupted quietly, “But I’m white.”

Reading on further, Pethel saw that Thisbe Olt’s satellite had grossed a billion U.S. dollars in 2079. Wow, he said to himself. That’s big business, Before him was a pic of Thisbe; with cadmium-white hair and little high conical breasts she was a superb sight, an aesthetic as well as a sexual treat. The pic showed her serving male guests of her satellite a tequila sour—an added fillip because tequila, being derived from the mescal plant, had long been illegal on Earth proper.

Pethel touched the word tab of Thisbe’s pic and at once Thisbe’s eyes sparkled, her head turned, her stable, dense breasts vibrated subtly, and in the balloon above her head the proper words formed.

Embarrassing personal urgency, Mr. American businessman? Do as many doctors recommend: visit my Golden Door!

It was an ad, Pethel discovered. Not an informative article.

“Excuse me.” A customer had entered the store and Hadley moved in his direction.

Oh lord, Darius Pethel thought as he recognized the customer. Don’t we have his ‘scuttler fixed yet? He rose to his feet, knowing that he would be personally needed to appease the man; this was Dr. Lurton Sands, and because of his recent domestic troubles he had become, of late, demanding and hot-tempered.

“Yes, Doctor,” Pethel said, walking toward him. “What can I do for you today?” As if he didn’t know. Trying to fight off Myra as well as keep his mistress, Cally Vale, Dr. Sands had enough problems; he really needed the use of his Jiffi−scuttler. Unlike other customers it was not going to be possible to put this man off.

Plucking by reflex at his great handlebar mustache, presidential candidate Jim Briskin said tentatively, “We’re in a rut, Sal. I ought to fire you. You’re trying to make me out the epitome of the Cols and yet you know I’ve spent twenty years playing up to the white power structure. Frankly, I think we’d have better luck trying to get the white vote, not the dark. I’m used to them; I can appeal to them.”

“You’re wrong,” his campaign manager, Salisbury Heim, said. “Your appeal—listen and understand this, Jim—is to the dark kid and his wife scared to death their only prospect is winding up bibs in some gov warehouse. “Bottled in bond,” as they say. In you these people see . . .”

“But I feel guilty.”

“Why?” Sal Heim demanded.

“Because I’m a fake. I can’t close the Dept of SPW warehouses; you know that. You got me to promise, and ever since I’ve been sweating my life away trying to conceive how it could be done. And there isn’t any way.” He examined his wristwatch; one quarter-hour remained before he had to give his speech. “Have you read the speech Phil Danville wrote for me?” He reached into his disorganized, lumpy coat-pouch.

“Danville!” Heim’s face convulsed. “I thought you got rid of him; give me that.” He grabbed the folded sheets and began going over them. “Danville is a nut. Look.” He waved the first sheet in Jim Briskin’s face. “According to him, you’re going to ban traffic from the U.S. to Thisbe’s satellite. That’s insane! If the Golden Door is closed, the birth rate will jump back up again where it was— what then? How does Danville manage to counter that?”

After a pause Briskin said, “The Golden Door is immoral.”

Spluttering, Heim said, “Sure. And animals should wear pants.”

“There’s just got to be a better solution than that satellite.”

Heim lapsed into silence as he read further into title speech. “And he has you advocate this outmoded, thoroughly discredited planet-wetting technique of Bruno Mini.” He tossed the papers into Jim Briskin’s lap. “So what do you wind up with? You back a planetary colonization scheme tried twenty years ago and abandoned; you advocate closing the Golden Door satellite—you’ll be popular, Jim, after tonight. But popular with whom, though? Just answer me; who is this aimed at?” He waited.

There was silence.

“You know what I think?” Heim said presently. “I think this is your elaborate way of giving up. Of saying to hell with the whole thing. It’s how you shed responsibility; I saw you start to do the same thing at the convention in that crazy doomsday speech you gave, that morbid curiosity which still has everyone baffled. But fortunately you’d already been nominated. It was too late for the convention to repudiate you.”

Briskin said, “I expressed my real convictions in that speech.”

“What, that civilization is now doomed because of this overpopulation biz? Some convictions for the first Col President to have.” Heim got to his feet and walked to the window; he stood looking out at downtown Philadelphia, at tide jet-copters landing, the runnels of autocars and ramps of footers coming and going, into and out of every high-rise building in sight. “I once in a while think,” Heim said in a low voice, “that you feel it’s doomed because it’s nominated a Negro and may elect him; it’s a way of putting yourself down.”

“No,” Briskin said, with calm; his long face remained unruffled.

“I’ll tell you what to say in your speech for tonight,” Heim said, his back to Briskin. “First, you once more describe your relationship with Frank Woodbine, because people go for space explorers; Woodbine is a hero, much more so than you or what’s-his-name. You know; the man you’re running against. The SRCD incumbent.”

“William Schwarz.”

Heim nodded exaggeratedly. “Yes, you’re right. Then after you gas about Woodbine—and we show a few shots of you and him standing together on various planets—then you make a joke about Dr. Sands.”

“No,” Briskin said.

“Why not? Is Sands a sacred cow? You ain’t touch him?”

Jim Briskin said slowly, painstakingly, “Because Sands is a great doctor and shouldn’t be ridiculed in the media the way he is right now.”

“He saved your brother’s life. By finding him a wet new liver just in the nick of time. Or he saved your mother just when . . .”

“Sands has preserved hundreds, thousands, of people. Including plenty of Cols. Whether they were able to pay or not.” Briskin was silent a moment and then he added, “Also I met his wife Myra and I didn’t like her. Years ago I went to her; I had made a girl preg and we wanted abort advice.”

“Good!” Heim said violently. “We can use that. You made a girl pregnant—that, when Nonovulid is free for the asking; that shows you’re a provident type, Jim.” He tapped his forehead. “You think ahead.”

“I now have five minutes,” Briskin said woodenly. He gathered up the pages of Phil Danville’s speech and returned them to his inside coat pouch; he still wore a formal dark suit even in hot weather. That, and a flaming red wig, had been his trademark back in the days when he had telecast as a TV newsclown.

“Give that speech,” Heim said, “and you’re politically dead. And if you’re . . .” He broke off. The door to the room had opened and his wife Patricia stood there.

“Sorry to bother you,” Pat said. “But everyone out here can hear you yelling.” Heim caught a glimpse, then, of the big outside room full of teen-age Briskinettes, uniformed young volunteers who had come from all over the country to help elect the Republican Liberal candidate.

“Sorry,” Heim murmured.

Pat entered the room and shut the door after her. “I think Jim’s right, Sal.” Small, gracefully-built— she had once been a dancer—Pat lithely seated herself and lit a cigar. “The more naive Jim appears, the better.” She blew gray smoke from between her luminous, pale lifts. “He still has a lingering reputation for being cynical. Whereas he should be another Wendell Wilkie.”

“Wilkie lost,” Heim pointed out.

“And Jim may lose,” Pat said; she tossed her head, brushing back her long hair from her eyes. “But if he does, he can run again and win next time. The important thing is for him to appear sensitive and innocent, a sweet person who takes the world’s suffering on his own shoulders because he’s made that way. He can’t help it; he has to suffer. You see?”

“Amateurs,” Heim said, and groaned.

The TV cameras stood inert, as the seconds passed, but they were ready to begin; the time for the speech lay just ahead as Jim Briskin sat at the small desk which he employed when addressing the people. Before him, near at hand, rested Phil Danville’s speech. And he sat meditating as the TV technicians prepared for the recording.

The speech would be beamed to the Republican−Liberal Party’s satellite relay station and from it telecast repeatedly until saturation point had been achieved. States Rights Conservative Democrat attempts to jam it would probably fail, because of the enormous signal-strength of the R−L satellite. The message would get through despite Tompkins Act, which permitted jamming of political material. And, simultaneously, Schwarz’ speech would be jammed in return; it was scheduled for release at the same time.

Across from him sat Patricia Heim, lost in a cloud of nervous introspection. And, in the control room, he caught a glimpse of Sal, busy with the TV engineers, making certain that the image recorded would be flattering.

And, off in a corner by himself, sat Phil Danville. No one talked to Danville; the party bigwigs, passing in and out of the studio, astutely ignored his existence.

A technician nodded to Jim. Time to begin his speech.

“It’s very popular these days,” Jim Briskin said to the TV camera, “to make fun of the old dreams and schemes for planetary colonization. How could people have been so nutty? Trying to live in completely inhuman environments . . . on worlds never designed for Homo sapiens. And it’s amusing that they tried for decades to alter these hostile environments to meet human needs—and naturally failed.” He spoke slowly, almost drawlingly; he took his time. He had the attention of the nation, and he meant to make thorough use of it. “So now we’re looking for a planet readymade, another ‘Venus’, or more accurately what Venus specifically never was. What we had hoped it would be: lush, moist and verdant and productive, a Garden of Eden just waiting for us to show up.”

Reflectively, Patricia Heim smoked her El Producto alta cigar, never taking her eyes from him.

“Well,” Jim Briskin said, “we’ll never find it. And if we do, it’ll be too late. Too small, too late, too far away. If we want another Venus, a planet we can colonize, we’ll have to manufacture it ourselves. We can laugh ourselves sick at Bruno Mini, but the fact is, he was right.”

In the control room Sal Heim stared at him in gross anguish. He had done it. Sanctioned Mini’s abandoned scheme of recasting the ecology of another world. Madness revisited.

The camera clicked off.

Turning his head, Jim Briskin saw the expression on Sal Heim’s face. He had been cut off there in the control room; Sal had given the order.

“You’re not going to let me finish?” Jim said.

Sal’s voice, amplified, boomed, “No, goddam it. No!”

Standing up, Pat called back, “You have to. He’s the candidate. If he wants to hang himself, let him.”

Also on his feet, Danville said hoarsely, “If you cut him off again I’ll spill it publicly. I’ll leak the entire thing how you’re working him like a puppet!” He started at once toward the door of the studio; he was leaving. Evidently he meant what he had said.

Jim Briskin said, “You better turn it back on, Sal. They’re right; you have to let me talk.” He did not feel angry, only impatient. His desire was to continue, nothing else. “Come on, Sal,” he said quietly. “I’m waiting.”

The party brass and Sal Heim, in the control room, conferred.

“He’ll give in,” Pat said to Jim Briskin. “I know Sal.” Her face was expressionless; she did not enjoy this, but she intended to endure it.

“Right,” Jim agreed, nodding.

“But will you watch a playback of the speech, Jim?” She said, “For Sal’s sake. Just to be sure you intend what you say.”

“Sure,” he said. He had meant to anyhow.

Sal Heim’s voice boomed from the wall speaker. “Damn your black Col hide, Jim!”

Grinning, Jim Briskin waited, seated at his desk, his arms folded.

The read light of the central camera clicked back on.

After the speech Jim Briskin’s press secretary, Dorothy Gill, collared him in the corridor. “Mr. Briskin, you asked me yesterday to find out if Bruno Mini is still alive. He is, after a fashion.”

Miss Gill examined her notes. “He’s a buyer for a dried fruit company in Sacramento, California, now. Evidently Mini’s entirely given up his planet-wetting career, but your speech just now will probably bring him back to his old grazing ground.”

“Possibly not,” Briskin said. “Mini may not like the idea of a Col taking up his ideas and propagandizing them. Thanks, Dorothy.”

Coming up beside him, Sal Heim shook his head and said, “Jim, you just don’t have political instinct.”

Shrugging, Jim Briskin said, “Possibly you’re right.” He was in that sort of mood, now he felt passive and depressed. In any case the damage had been done; the speech was on tape and already being relayed to the R−L satellite. His review of it had been cursory at best.

“I heard what Dotty said,” Sal said. “That Mini character will be showing up here now; we’ll have him to contend with, along with all our other problems. Anyhow, how about a drink?”

“Okay,” Jim Briskin agreed. “Wherever you say. Lead the way.”

“May I join you?” Patricia said, appearing beside her husband.

“Sure, “Sal said. He put his arm around her and hugged her. “A good big tall one, full of curiouslyrefreshing tiny little bubbles that last all through the drink. Just what women like.”

As they stepped out onto the sidewalk, Jim Briskin saw a picket—two of them, in fact—carrying signs.

KEEP THE

WHITE HOUSE WHITE

LET’S KEEP AMERICA CLEAN!

The two pickets, both young Caucs, stared at him and he and Sal and Patricia stared at them. No one spoke. Several homeopape camera men snapped picks; their flashbulbs lit the static scene starkly for an instant, and then Sal and Patricia, with Jim Briskin following, started on. The two pickets continued to pace back and forth along their little routes.

“The bastards,” Pat said as the three of them sealed themselves at a booth in the cocktail lounge across the street from the TV studio.

Jim Briskin said, “It’s their job. God evidently meant them to do that.” It did not particularly bother him; in one form or another it had been a part of his life as long as he could remember.

“But Schwarz agreed to keep race and religion out of the election,” Pat said.

“Bill Schwarz did,” Jim Briskin said, “but Verne Engel didn’t. And it’s Engel who runs CLEAN, not the SRCD Party.”

“I know darn well the SRCD pays the money to keep CLEAN solvent,” Sal murmured. “Without their support it’d fold in a day.”

“I don’t agree with you,” Briskin said. “I think there’ll always be a hate organization like CLEAN, and there’ll always be people to support it.” After all, CLEAN had a point; they did not want to see a Negro President, and wasn’t it their right to feel like that? Some people did, some people didn’t; that was perfectly natural. And, he thought, why should we pretend that race is not the issue? It is, really. I am a Negro. Verne Engel is factually correct. The real question was: how large a percentage of the electorate supported CLEAN’S views? Certainly, CLEAN did not hurt his feelings; he could not be wounded; he had experienced too much already in his years as a newsclown. In my years, he thought to himself acidly, as an American Negro.

A small boy, white, appeared at the booth with a pen and tablet of paper. “Mr. Briskin, can I get your autograph?”

Jim signed and the boy darted off to join his parents at the door of the tavern. The couple, welldressed, young, and obviously upper stratum, waved at him cheerily. “We’re with you!” the man called.

“Thanks,” Jim said, nodding to them and trying—but not successfully—to sound cheery in return.

“You’re in a mood,” Pat commented.

He nodded. Mutely.

“Think of all those people with lily-white skins,” Sal said, “who’re going to vote for a Col. My, my. It’s encouraging. Proves not all of us Whites are bad down underneath.”

“Did I ever say you were?” Jim asked.

“No, but you really think that. You don’t really trust any of us.”

“Where’d you drag that up from?” Jim demanded, angry now.

“What’re you going to do?” Sal said. “Slash me with your electro-graphic magnetic razor?”

Pat said sharply, “What are you doing, Sal? Why are you talking to Jim like that?” She peered about nervously. “Suppose someone overheard.”

“I’m trying to jerk him out of his depression,” Sal said. “I don’t like to see him give in to them. Those CLEAN pickets upset him, but he doesn’t recognize it or feel it consciously.” He eyed Jim.

“I’ve heard you say it many times. ‘I can’t be hurt.’ Hell, you sure can. You were hurt just now. You want everyone to love you, White and Col both. I don’t know how you ever got into politics in the first place. You should have stayed a newsclown, delighting young and old. Especially the very young.”

Jim said, “I want to help the human race.”

“By changing the ecology of the planets? Are you serious?”

“If I’m voted into office I actually intend to appoint Bruno Mini, without even having met him, director of the space program; I’m going to give him the chance they never let him have, even when they—”

“If you get elected,” Pat said, “you can pardon Dr. Sands.”

“Pardon him?” He glanced at her, disconcerted . . . “He’s not being tried; he’s being divorced.”

“You haven’t heard the rumes?” Pat said. “His wife is going to dig up something criminal he’s done so she can dispatch him and obtain their total property. No one knows what it is yet but she’s hinted—”

“I don’t want to hear,” Jim Briskin said.

“You may be right,” Pat said thoughtfully. “The Sands divorce is turning nasty; it might backfire if you mentioned it, as Sal wants you to. The mistress, Cally Vale, has disappeared, possibly murdered. Maybe you do have an instinct, Jim. Maybe you don’t need us after all.”

“I need you,” Jim said, “but not to embroil me in Dr. Sands’ marital problems.” He sipped his drink.

Rick Erickson, repairman for Pethel Jiffi−scuttler Sales & Service, lit a cigarette, tipped his stool back by pushing with his bony knees against his work bench. Before him rested the master turret of a defective Jiffi−scuttler. The one, in fact, which belonged to Dr. Lurton Sands.

There had always been bugs in the ‘scuttlers. This first one put in use had broken down; years ago, that had been, but the ‘scuttlers remained basically the same now as then.

Historically, the original defective ‘scuttler had belonged to an employee of Terran Development named Henry Ellis. After the fashion of humans Ellis had not reported the defect to his employers . . . or so Rick recalled. It had been before his time but myth persisted, an incredible legend, still current among ‘scuttler repairmen, that through the defect in his ‘scuttler Ellis had—it was hard to believe—composed the Holy Bible.

The principle underlying the operation of the ‘scuttlers was a limited form of time travel. Along the tube of his ‘scuttler—it was said—Ellis had found a weak point, a shimmer at which another continuum completely had been visible. He had stooped down and witnessed a gathering of tiny persons who yammered in speeded-up voices and scampered about in their world just beyond the wall of the tube.

Who were these people? Initially, Ellis had not known, but even so he had engaged in commerce with them; he had accepted sheets—astonishingly thin and tiny—of questions, taken the questions to language-decoding equipment at TD, then, once the foreign script of the tiny people had been translated, taking the questions to one of the corporation’s big computers to get them answered.

Then back to the Linguistics Department and at last at the end of the day, back up the tube of the Jiffi−scuttler to hand to the tiny people the answers—in their own language—to their questions.

Evidently, if you believed this, Ellis had been a charitable man.

However, Ellis had supposed that this was a non-Terran race dwelling on a miniature planet in some other system entirely. He was wrong. According to the legend, the tiny people were from Earth’s own past; the script, of course, had been ancient Hebrew. Whether this had really happened Rick did not pretend to know, but, in any case, for some breach of company rules Ellis had been fired by TD and had long since disappeared. Perhaps he had emigrated; who knew?

Who cared? TD’s job was to patch the thin spot in the tube and see that the defect did not reoccur in subsequent ‘scuttlers.

All at once the intercom at the end of Rick’s workbench blared. “Hey, Erickson.” It was Pethel’s voice. “Dr. Sands is up here asking about his ‘scuttler. When’ll it be ready?”

With the handle of a screwdriver Rick Erickson savagely tapped the master turret of Dr. Sands’ ‘scuttler. I better go upstairs and talk to Sands, he reflected. I mean, this is driving me crazy. It can’t malfunction the way he claims.

Two steps at a time, Rick Erickson ascended to the main floor. There, at the front door, a man was just leaving; it was Sands—Erickson recognized him from the homeopape pics. He hurried, reached him outside on the sidewalk.

“Listen, doc—how come you say your ‘scuttler dumps you off in Portland, Oregon and places like that? It just can’t; it isn’t built that way!”

They stood facing each other. Dr. Sands, well-dressed, lean and slightly balding, with deeply tanned skin and a thin, tapered nose, regarded him complexly, cautious about answering. He looked smart, very smart.

So this is the man they’re all writing about, Erickson said to himself. Carries himself better than the rest of us and has a suit made from Martian mole cricket hide. But—he felt irritation. Dr. Sands in general had a helpless manner; good-looking, in his mid-forties, he had an easy-going, bewildered geniality about him, as if unable to deal with or comprehend the forces which had overtaken him. Erickson could see that; Dr. Sands had a crushed quality, still stunned.

And yet Sands remained a gentleman. In a quiet, reasonable tone he said, “But that’s what it seems to do I wish I could tell you more, but I’m not mechanically inclined.” He smiled, a thoroughly disarming smile that made Erickson ashamed of his own gruffness.

“Aw, hell,” Erickson said, backtracking. “It’s the fault of TD—they could have ironed the bugs out of the ‘scuttlers years ago. Too bad you got a lemon.” You look like a not too bad guy, he reflected.

“‘A lemon,’” Dr. Sands echoed. “Yes, that sums it up.” His face twisted; he seemed amused. “Well, that’s my luck. Everything has been running like this for me, lately.”

“Maybe I could get TD to take it back,” Erickson said. “And swap you another one for it.”

“No.” Dr. Sands shook his head vigorously. “I want that particular one.” His tone had become firm; he meant what he said.

“Why?” Who would want to keep an admitted lemon? It didn’t make sense. In fact, the entire business had a wrong ring to it, and Erickson’s keen faculties detected this—he had seen many, many customers in his time.

“Because it’s mine,” Sands said. “I picked it out originally.” He started on, then, down the sidewalk.

“Don’t give me that,” Erickson said, half to himself.

Pausing, Sands said, “What?” He moved a step back, his face dark, now. The geniality had departed.

“Sorry. No offense.” Erickson eyed Dr. Sands acutely. And did not like what he saw. Beneath the doctor’s suavity there lay a coldness, something fixed and hard. This was no ordinary person, and Erickson felt uneasy.

Dr. Sands said in a crisp voice, “Get it fixed and soon.” He turned and strode on down the sidewalk, leaving Erickson standing there.

“Jeez,” Erickson said to himself, and whistled. “My busted back. I wouldn’t want to tangle with him, he thought as he walked into the store.”

Going downstairs a step at a time, hands thrust deep in his pockets, he thought: Maybe I’ll stick it all back together and take a trip through it. He was again thinking of old Henry Ellis, the first man to receive a defective ‘scuttler; he was recalling that Ellis had not wanted to give up his particular one, either. And for good reason.

Back in the service department basement once more, Rick seated himself at the work bench, picked up Dr. Sands’ ‘scuttler-turret and began to reassemble it. Presently, he had expertly restored it to its place and had hooked it back into the circuit.

Now, he said to himself as he switched on the power field. Let’s see where it gets us. He entered the big gleaming circular hoop which was the entrance of the ‘scuttler, found himself—as usual—within a gray, formless tube which stretched in both directions. Framed in the opening behind him lay his work bench, And in front of him?

New York City. An unstable view of an industriously-active street corner which bordered Dr. Sands’ office. And a wedge, beyond it, of the vast building itself, the high rise skyscraper of plastic—rexeroid compounds from Jupiter—with its infinitude of floors, endless windows . . . and, past that, monojets rising and descending from the ramps, along which the footers scurried in swarms so dense as to seem self-destructive. The largest city in the world, four-fifths of which lay subsurface; what he saw was only a meager fraction, a trace of its visible projections. No one in his lifetime, even a jerry, could view it all; the city was simply too extensive.

See? Erickson grumbled to himself. Your ‘scuttler’s working okay; this isn’t Portland, Oregon— it’s exactly what it’s supposed to be.

Crouching down, Erickson ran an expert hand over tide surface of the tube. Seeking—what? He didn’t know. But something which would justify the doctor’s insistence on retaining this particular ‘scuttler.

He took his time. He was not in a hurry. And he intended to find what he was searching for.

The planet-wetting speech which Jim Briskin delivered that night—taped earlier during the day and then beamed from the R−L satellite—was too painful for Salisbury Heim to endure.

Therefore, he took an hour off and sought relief as many men did: he boarded a jet’ab and shortly was on his way to the Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite. Let Jim blab away about Bruno Mini’s crackpot engineering program, he said to himself as he rested in the rear seat of the rising ‘ab, grateful for this interval of relaxation. Let him cut his own throat. But at least I don’t have to be dragged down to defeat along with him; I’m tempted, sometime before election day, to cut myself loose and go over to the SRCD party.

Beyond doubt, Bill Schwarz would take him on. By an intricate route Heim had already sounded the opposition out. Schwarz had, through this careful, indirect linkage, expressed pleasure at the idea of Heim joining forces with him. However, Heim was not really ready to make his move; he had not pursued the topic further.

At least, not until today. This new, painful bombshell. And at a time when the party had troubles enough already.

The fact of the matter was—and he knew this from the latest polls—that Jim Briskin was trailing Schwarz. Despite the fact that he had all the Col vote, and that included non-Negro dark races such as Puerto Ricans on the East Coast and the Mexicans on the West. It was not a shoo-in by any means. And why was Briskin trailing? Because all the Whites would be going to the polls, whereas only about sixty per cent of the Cols would show up on election day. Incredibly, they were apathetic toward Jim. Perhaps they believed—and he had heard this said—that Jim had sold out to the White power structure. That he was not authentically a leader of the Col people as such. And in a sense this was true.

Because Jim Briskin represented Whites and Cols alike.

“We’re there, sir,” the ‘ab driver, a Col, informed him. The “ab slowed, came to rest on the breastshaped vehicle port of the satellite, a dozen yards from the pink nipple which served as a location-signal device. “You’re Jim Briskin’s campaign manager?” the driver said, turning to face him.; “Yeah, I recognize you. Listen, Mr. Heim; he’s not a sell-out, is he? I heard a lot of folk argue that, but he wouldn’t do it; I know that.”

“Jim Briskin,” Heim said as he dug for his wallet “has sold out nobody. And never will. You can tell your buddies that because it’s the truth.” He paid his fare, feeling grumpy. Grumpy as hell.

“But is it true that?”

“He’s working with Whites, yes. He’s working with me and I’m White. So what? Are the Whites supposed to disappear when Briskin is elected? Is that what you want? Because if it is, you’re not going to get it.”

“I see what you mean, I guess,” the driver said, nodding slowly. “You infer he’s for all the people, right? He’s got the interest of the White minority at heart just like tie has the Col majority. He’s going to protect everybody, even including you Whites.”

“That’s right,” Salisbury Heim said, as he opened the ‘ab’s door. “As you put it, ‘even including you Whites’.” He stepped out on the pavement. Yes, even us, he said to himself. Because we merit it.

“Hello there, Mr. Heim.” A woman’s melodious voice. Heim turned—

“Thisbe,” he said, pleased. “How are you?”

“I’m glad to see that you haven’t stayed below just because your candidate disapproves of us,” Thisbe Olt said. Archly, she raised her green-painted, shining eyebrows. Her narrow, harlequinlike face glinted with countless dots of pure light embedded within her skin; it gave her eerie, nimbus-like countenance the appearance of constantly-renewed beauty. And she had renewed herself, over a number of decades. Willowy, almost frail, she fiddled with a tassel of stoneimpregnated fabric draped about her bare arms; she had put on gay clothes in order to come out and greet him and he was gratified. He liked her very much—had for some time now.

Guardedly, Sal Heim said, “What makes you think Jim Briskin has any bones to pick with the Golden Door, Thisbe? Has he ever actually said anything to that effect?” As far as he knew,

Jim’s opinions on that topic had not been made public; at least he had tried to keep them under wraps.

“We know these things, Sal,” Thisbe said, “I think you’d better go inside and talk with George Walt about it; they’re down on level C, in their office. They have a few things to say to you, Sal. I know because they’ve been discussing it.”

Annoyed, Sal said, “I didn’t come here—” But what was the use? If the owners of the Golden Door satellite wanted to see him, it was undoubtedly advisable for him to come around. “Okay,” he said, and followed Thisbe in the direction of the elevator.

It always distressed him—despite his efforts to the contrary—to find himself engaged in conversation with George Walt. They were a mutation of a special sort; he had never seen anything quite like them. Nonetheless, although handicapped, George Walt had risen to great economic power in this society. The Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite, it was rumored, was only one of their holdings; they were spread extensively over the financial map of the modern world. They were a form of mutated twinning, joined at the base of the skull so that a single cephalic structure served both separate bodies. Evidently the personality George inhabited one hemisphere of the brain, made use of one eye: the right, as he recalled. And the personality Walt existed on the other side, distinct with its own idiosyncrasies, views and drives—and its own eye from which to view the outside universe.

A uniformed attendant, a sort of cop, stopped Sid, as the elevator doors opened on level C.

“Mr. George Walt wanted to see me,” Sal said. “Or so Miss Olt tells me, at least.”

“This way, Mr. Heim,” the uniformed attendant said, touching his cap respectfully and leading Sal down the carpeted, silent hall.

He was let into a large chamber—and there, on a couch, sat George Walt. Both bodies at once rose to their feet, supporting between them the common head. The head, containing the unmingled entities of tide brothers, nodded in greeting and the mouth smiled. One eye—the left—regarded him steadily, while the other wandered vaguely off, as if preoccupied.

The two necks joined the head in such a way that the head and face were tilted slightly back.

George Walt tended to look slightly over whomever they were talking to, and this added to the unique impression; it made them seem formidable, as if their attention could not really be engaged. The head was normal size, however, as were both bodies. The body to the left—Sal did not recall which of them it was—wore informal clothing, a cotton shirt and slacks, with sandals on the feet. The right hand body, however, was formally dressed in a single-breasted suit, tie and buttoned gray cape. And the hands of the right body were jammed deep into the trouser pockets, a stance which gave to it an aura of authority if not age; it seemed distinctly older than its twin.

“This is George,” the head said, pleasantly. “How are you, Sal Heim? Good to see you.” The left body extended its hand. Sal walked toward the two of them and gingerly shook hands. The right hand body, Walt, did not want to shake with him; its hands remained in its pockets.

“This is Walt,” the head said, less pleasantly, then. “We wanted to discuss your candidate with you, Together, the two bodies managed to walk to the sideboard, where an elaborate bar could be seen. Walt’s hands opened a bottle of Bourbon while George’s expertly fixed an old fashioned, mixed sugar and water and bitters together in the bottom of a glass. Together, George Walt made the drink and carried it back to Sal.

“Thanks,” Sal Heim said, accepting the drink.

“This is Walt,” the common head said to him. “We know that if Jim Briskin is elected he’ll instruct his Attorney General to find ways to shut the satellite down. Isn’t that a fact?” The two eyes, together now, fixed themselves on him in an intense, astute gaze.

“I don’t know where you heard that,” Sal said, evasively.

“This is Walt,” the head said. “There’s a leak in your organization; that’s where we heard it. You realize what this means. We’ll have to throw our support behind Schwarz. And you know how many transmissions we make to Earth in a single day.”

Sal sighed. The Golden Door kept a perpetual stream of junk, honky-tonk stag-type shows, pouring down over a variety of channels, available to and widely watched by almost everyone in the country. The shows—especially the climactic orgy in which Thisbe herself, with her famous display of expanding and contracting muscles working in twenty directions simultaneously and in four colors, appeared—were a come-on for the activity of the satellite. But it would be duck soup to work in an anti-Briskin bias; the satellite’s announcers were slick prose.

Downing his drink he rose and started toward the door. “Go ahead and stick your stag shows on Jim; we’ll win the election anyhow and then you can be sure he’ll shut you. In fact, I personally guarantee it right now.”

The head looked uneasy. “Dirty p-pool,” it stammered.

Sal shrugged. “I’m just protecting the interests of my client; you’ve been making threats toward him. You started it, both of you.”

“This is George,” the head said rapidly. “Here’s what I think we ought to have. Listen to this, Walt. We want Jim Briskin to come up here to the Golden Door and be photographed publicly.” It added, in applause for itself, “Good idea. Get it, Sal? Briskin arrives here, covered by all the media, and visits one of the girls; it’ll be good for his image because it’ll show he’s a normal guy—and not some creep. So you benefit from this. And, while he’s here, Briskin compliments us.” It added, “A good final touch but optional. For instance, he says the national interest has—”

“He’ll never do it,” Sal said. “He’ll lose the election first.”

The head said, plaintively, “We’ll give him any girl he wants; my lord, we have five thousand to choose from!”

“No luck,” Sal Heim said. “Now if you were to make that offer to me I’d take you up on it in a second. But not Jim. He’s—old-fashioned.” That was as good a way to put it as any. “He’s a Puritan. You can call him a remnant of the twentieth century, if you want.”

“Or nineteenth,” the head said, venomously.

“Say anything you want,” Sal said, nodding. “Jim won’t care. He knows what he believes in; he thinks the satellite is undignified. The way it’s all handled up here, boom, boom, boom—mechanically, with no personal touch, no meeting of humans on a human basis. You run an autofac; I don’t object and most people don’t object, because it saves times. But Jim does, because he’s sentimental.”

Two right arms gestured at Sal menacingly as the head said loudly, “The hell with that! We’re as sentimental up here as you can get! We play background music in every room—the girls always learn the customer’s first name and they’re required to call him by that and nothing else! How sentimental can you get, for chrissakes? “What do you want?” In a higher-pitched voice it roared on, “A marriage ceremony before and then a divorce procedure afterward, so it constitutes a legal marriage, is that it? Or do you want us to teach the girls to sew mother hubbards and bloomers, and you pay to see their ankles, and that’s it? Listen, Sal.” Its voice dropped a tone, became ominous and deadly “Listen, Sal Heim,” it repeated. “We know our business; don’t tell us our business and we won’t tell you yours. Starting tonight our TV announcers are going to insert a plug for Schwarz in every telecast to Earth, right in the middle of the glorious chef-d’oeuvre you know—what where the girls . . . well, you know. Yes, I mean that part. And we’re going to make a campaign out of this, really put it over. We’re going to insure Bill Schwarz’ reelection.” It added,

“And insure that Col fink’s thorough, total defeat.”

Sal said nothing. The great carpeted office was silent.

“No response from you, Sal? You’re going to sit idly by?”

“I came up here to visit a girl I like,” Sal said. “Sparky Rivers, her name is. I’d like to see her now.”

He felt weary. “She’s different from all the others . . . at least, all I’ve tried.” Rubbing his forehead he murmured, “No, I’m too tired, now. I’ve changed my mind. I’ll just leave.”

“If she’s as good as you say,” the head said, “it won’t require any energy from you.” It laughed in appreciation of its wit. “Send a fray named Sparky Rivers down here,” it instructed, pressing a button on its desk.

Sal Heim nodded dully. There was something to that. And after all, this was what he had come here for, this ancient, appreciated remedy.

“You’re working too hard,” the head said acutely. “What’s the matter, Sal? Are you losing? Obviously, you need our help. Very badly, in fact.”

“Help, schmelp,” Sal said. “What I need is a six-week rest, and not up here. I ought to take an “ab to Africa and hunt spiders or whatever the craze is right now.” With all his problems, he had lost touch. Those big trench-digging spiders are out, now,” the head informed him. “Now it’s nocturnal moths, again.” Walt’s right arm pointed at the wall and Sal saw, behind glass, three enormous iridescent cadavers, displayed under an ultraviolet lamp which brought out all their many colors.

“Caught them myself,” the head said, and then chided itself. “No, you didn’t; I did, You saw them but I popped them into the killing jar.”

Sal Heim sat silently waiting for Sparky Rivers, as the two inhabitants of the head argued with each other as to which of them had brought back the African moths.

The top-notch and expensive—and dark-skinned—private investigator, Tito Cravelli, operating out of N’York, handed the woman seated across from him the findings which his Altac 3−60 computer had derived from the data provided it. It was a good machine.

“Forty hospitals,” Tito said. “Forty transplant operations within last year. Statistically, it’s unlikely that the UN Vital Organ Fund Reserve would have had that many organs available in so limited a time, but it is possible. In other words, we’ve got nothing.”

Mrs. Myra Sands smoothed her skirt thoughtfully, then lit a cigarette. “We’ll select at random from among the forty; I want you to follow at least five or six up. How long will it take for you to do that?”

Tito calculated silently. “Say two days. If I have to go there and see people. Of course, if I can do some of it on the phone-” He liked to work through the Vidphone Corporation of America’s product; it meant he could stick near the Altac 3-60. And, when anything came up, he could feed the data on the spot, get an opinion without delay. He respected the 3-60; it had set him back a great deal, a year ago when he had purchased it. And he did not intend to permit it to lie idle, not if he could help it. But sometimes—

This was a difficult situation. Myra Sands was; not the sort who could endure uncertainty; for her things had to be either this or that, either A or not-A—Myra made use of Aristotle’s Law of the Excluded Middle like no one else he knew. He admired her. Myra was a handsome, extremely well-educated woman, light-haired, in her middle forties; across from him she sat erect and trim in her yellow Lunar squeak-frog suit, her legs long and without defect. Her sharp chin alone let on—to Tito at least—the grimness, the no-nonsense aspect, of her personality. Myra was a businesswoman first, before anything else; as one of the nation’s foremost authorities in the field of therapeutic abortions, she was highly paid and highly honored . . . and she was well aware of this. After all, she had been at it for years. And Tito respected anyone who lived as an independent business person; after all, he, too, was his own boss, beholden to no one, to no subsidizing organization or economic entity. He and Myra had something in common. Although, of course, Myra would have denied it, Myra Sands was a terrible goddam snob; to her, Tito Cravelli was an employee whom she had hired to find out—or rather to establish as fact -certain information about her husband.

He could not imagine why Lurton Sands had married her. Surely it had been conflict— psychological, social, sexual, professional—from the start.

However, there was no explaining the chemistry which joined men and women, locked them in embraces of hate and mutual suffering sometimes for ninety years on end. In his line, Tito had seen plenty of it, enough to last him even a jerry lifetime.

“Call Lattimore Hospital in San Francisco,” Myra instructed in her crisp, vigilantly authoritative voice. “In August, Lurton transplanted a spleen for an army major, there; I think his name was Walleck or some such quiddity as that. I recall, at the time . . . Lurton had had, what shall I say? A little too much to drink. It was evening and we were having dinner. Lurton blurted out some darn thing or other. About ‘paying heavily’ for the spleen. You know, Tito, that VOFR prices are rigidly set by the UN and they’re not high; in fact they’re too low . . . that’s the cardinal reason the fund runs out of certain vital organs so often. Not from a lack of supply so much as the existence of too darn many takers.”

“Hmm,” Tito said, jotting notes.

“Lurton always said that if the VOFR only were to raise its rates . . .”

“You’re positive it was a spleen?” Tito broke in.

“Yes.” Myra nodded curtly, exhaling streamers of gray smoke that swirled toward the lamp behind her, a cloud that drifted in the artificial light of the office. It was dark outside, now; the time was seven-thirty.

“A spleen,” Tito recapitulated. “In August of this year. At Lattimore General Hospital in San Francisco. An army major named—”

“Now I’m beginning to think it was Wozzeck,” Myra put in. “Or is that an opera composer?”

“It’s an opera,” Tito said. “By Berg. Seldom performed, now.” He lifted the receiver of the vidphone. “I’ll get hold of the business office at Lattimore; it’s only four-thirty out there on the Coast.”

Myra rose to her feet and roamed restlessly about the office, rubbing her gloved hands together in a motion that irritated Tito and made it difficult for him to concentrate on his call.

“Have you had dinner?” he asked her, as he waited on the line.

“No. But I never eat until eight-thirty or nine; it’s barbaric to eat any earlier.”

Tito said, “Can I take you to dinner, Mrs. Sands? I know an awfully good little Armenian place in the Village. The food’s actually prepared by humans.”

“Humans? As compared to what?”

“Automatic food-processing systems,” Tito murmured. “Or don’t you ever eat in autoprep restaurants?” After all, the Sands were wealthy; possibly they normally enjoyed human-prepared food. “Personally, I can’t stand autopreps. The food’s always so predictable. Never burned, never . . .” He broke off; on the vidscreen the miniature features of an employee at Lattimore had formed. “Miss, this is Life-factors Research Consultants of N’York calling. I’d like to inquire about an operation performed on a Major Wozzeck or Walleck last August, a spleen transplant.”

“Wait,” Myra said suddenly. “Now I remember; it wasn’t a spleen—it was an islands of Langerhans; you know, that part of the pancreas which controls sugar production in the body. I remember because Lurton got to talking about it because he saw me putting two teaspoonfuls of sugar in my coffee.”

“I’ll look that up,” the girl at Lattimore said, overhearing Myra. She turned to her files.

“What I want to find out,” Tito said to her, “is the exact date at which the organ was obtained from the UN’s VOFR. If you can give me that datum, please.” He waited, accustomed to having to be patient. His line of work absolutely required that virtue, above all others, including intelligence.

The girl presently said, “A Colonel Weiswasser received an organ transplant on August twelve of this year. Islands of Langerhans, obtained from the VOFR the day before, August eleven. Dr. Lurton Sands performed the operation and of course certified the organ.”

“Thanks, miss,” Tito said, and broke the connection. “The VOFR office is closed,” Myra said, as he began once more to dial. “You’ll have to wait until tomorrow.”

“I know somebody there,” Tito said and continued dialing.

At last he had Gus Anderton, his contact at the UN’s vital organ bank. “Gus, this is Tito. Check August eleven this year for me. Islands of Langerhans; okay? See if the org-trans surgeon we previously had reference to picked up one there on that date.”

His contact was back almost at once with the information. “Correct, Tito; it all checks out. Aug eleven, Islands of Langerhans. Transferred by jet-hopper to Lattimore in San Francisco. Routine in every way.”

Tito Cravelli cut the circuit, exasperated.

After a pause Myra Sands, still pacing restlessly about his office, exclaimed, “But I know he’s been obtaining organs illegally. He never turned anybody down, and you know there never have been that many organs in the bank reserve—he had to get them somewhere else. He still is; I know it.”

“Knowing this and proving this are two . . .”

Turning to him, Myra snapped, “And outside of the UN bank there’s only one other place he would or could go.”

“Agreed,” Tito said, nodding. “But as your attorney said, you better have proof before you make the charge; otherwise he’ll sue you for slander, libel, defamation of character, the entire biz. He’d have to. You’d give him no choice.”

“You don’t like this,” Myra said.

Tito shrugged. “I don’t have to like it. That doesn’t matter.”

“But you think I’m treading on dangerous ground.”

“I know you are. Even if it’s true that Lurton Sands . . .”

“Don’t say ‘even if’. He’s a fanatic and you know it; he identifies so fully with his public image as a savior of lives that he’s simply had to make a psychological break with reality. Probably he started in a small way, with what he told himself was a unique situation, an exception; he had to have a particular organ and he took it. And the next time . . .” She shrugged. “It was easier. And so on.”

“I see, “Tito said.

“I think I see what we’re going to have to do,” Myra said. “What you’re going to have to do. Get started on-this. Find out from your contact at the UN exactly what organ the bank lacks at this time. Then deliberately set up another emergency situation; have someone in a hospital somewhere apply to Lurton for that particular transplant. I realize that it’ll cost one hell of a lot of money, but I’m willing to underwrite the expense. Do you see?”

“I see,” Tito said. In other words, trap Lurton Sands. Play on the man’s determination to save the life of a dying person . . . make his humanitarianism the instrument of his destruction. What a way to earn a living, Tito thought to himself. Another day, another dollar . . . it’s hardly that. Not when you get involved in something like this.

“I know you can arrange it,” Myra said to him fervently. “You’re good; you’re experienced. Aren’t you?”

“Yes, Mrs. Sands,” Tito said. I’m experienced. Yes, possibly I can trap the guy. Lead him by the nose. It shouldn’t be too hard.”

“Make sure your ‘patient’ offers him plenty,” Myra said in a bitter, taut voice. “Lurton will bite if he senses a good financial return; that’s what interests him—in spite of what you and the darn public may or may not imagine. I ought to know; I’ve lived with him a good many years, shared his most intimate thoughts.” She smiled, briefly. “It seems a shame I have to tell you how to go about your business, but obviously I have to.” Her smile returned, cold and exceedingly hard.

“I appreciate your assistance,” Tito said woodenly.

“No you don’t. You think I’m trying to do something wicked. Something out of mere spite.”

Tito said, “I don’t think anything; I’m just hungry. Maybe you don’t eat until eight-thirty or nine, but I have pyloric spasms and I have to eat by seven. Will you excuse me?” He rose to his feet, pushing his desk chair back. “I want to close up shop.” He did not renew his offer to take her out to dinner.

Gathering up her coat and purse, Myra Sands said, “Have you located Cally Vale and if so where?”

“No luck,” Tito said, and felt uncomfortable.

Staring at him, Myra said, “But why can’t you locate her? She must be somewhere! She looked as if she could not believe her ears.

“The court process servers can’t find her either,” Tito pointed out. “But I’m sure she’ll turn up by trial time.” He, too, had been wondering why his staff had been unable to locate Lurton Sands’ mistress; after all, there were only a limited number of places a person could hide, and detection and tracing devices, especially during the last two decades, had improved to an almost supernatural accuracy.

Myra said, “I’m beginning to think you’re just not any good. I wonder if I shouldn’t put my business in somebody else’s hands.”

“That’s your privilege,” Tito said. His stomach ached, a series of spasms of his pyloric valve. He wondered if he was ever going to get an opportunity to eat tonight.

“You must find Miss Vale,” Myra said. “She knows all the details of his activity; that’s why he’s got her hidden—in fact she’s pumping blood with a heart he procured for her.”

“Okay, Mrs. Sands,” Tito agreed, and inwardly winced at the growing pain . . .

The black-haired, extremely dark youth said shyly, “We came to you, Mrs. Sands, because we read about you in the homeopape. It said you were very good and also you take people without too much money.” He added, “We don’t have any money at all right now, but maybe we can pay you later.”

Brusquely, Myra Sands said, “Don’t worry about that now.” She surveyed the boy and girl. “Let’s see. Your names are Art and Rachael Chaffy. Sit down, both of you, and let’s talk, all right?” She smiled at them, her professional smile of greeting and warmth; it was reserved for her clients, given to no one else, not even to her husband—or, as she thought of Lurton now, her former husband.

In a soft voice the girl, Rachael, said “We tried to get them to let us become bibs but they said we should consult an advisor first.” She explained, “I’m—well, you see, somehow I got to be preg. I’m sorry.” She ducked her head fearfully, with shame, her cheeks flushing deep scarlet. “It’s too bad they don’t just let you kill yourself, like they did a few years ago,” she murmured. “Because that would solve it.”

“That law,” Myra said firmly, “was a bad idea. However imperfect deep-sleep is, it’s certainly preferable to the old form of self-destruction undertaken on an individual basis. How far advanced is your pregnancy, dear?”

“About a month and a half,” Rachael Chaffy said, lifting her head a trifle. She managed to meet Myra’s gaze; for a moment, at least.

“Then abort-processing presents no difficulty,” Myra said. “It’s routine. We can arrange for it by noon today and have it done by six tonight. At any one of several free government abort clinics here in the area. Just a moment.” Her secretary had opened the door to the office and was trying to catch her attention. “What is it, Tina?”

“An urgent phone call for you, Mrs. Sands.”

Myra clicked on her desk vidphone. On the screen Tito Cravelli’s features formed in replica, puffy with agitation.

“Mrs. Sands,” Tito said, “sorry to bother you at your office so early this morning. But a number of tracking devices we’ve been employing here have wound up their term of service and have come home. I thought you’d want to know. Cally Vale is nowhere on Earth. That’s absolutely been determined; that’s definite.” He was silent, then, waiting for her to say something.

“Then she emigrated,” Myra said, trying to picture the dainty and rather nauseatingly fragile Miss Vale in the rugged environment of Mars or Ganymede.

“No,” Tito Cravelli said emphatically, shaking his head. “We’ve checked on that, of course. Cally Vale did not emigrate. It doesn’t make sense, but there it is. No wonder we’re making no headway; we’re faced with an impossible situation.” He did not appear very happy about it. His features sagged glumly.

Myra said, “She’s not on Earth and she didn’t emigrate. Then she must . . .” It was obvious to her; why hadn’t they thought of it right away, when Cally originally vanished from sight? “She’s entered a government warehouse. Cally’s a bib.” It was the only possibility left.

“We’re looking into that,” Tito said, but without enthusiasm. “I admit it’s possible but frankly I just don’t buy it. Personally, I think they’ve thought up something new, something original; I’d stake my job on it, everything I have.” Tito’s tone was insistent, now. No longer hesitant. “But we’ll check all the Dept. of SPW warehouses, all ninety-four of them. That’ll take a couple of days at least. Meanwhile?” He caught sight of the young couple, the Chaffys, waiting silently. “Perhaps; I’d better discuss it with you later; there’s no urgency.”

Maybe what the homeopapes are hinting at actually did take place, Myra thought to herself.

Perhaps Lurton has actually killed her. So she can’t be subpoenaed by Frank Fenner at the trial.

“Do you believe Cally Vale is dead?” Myra said to Tito bluntly. She ignored the young couple seated opposite her; they did not at the moment matter; this was far too important.

“I’m in no position . . .” Tito began. Myra cut him off; she broke the connection, and the screen faded. I’m in no position to say, she finished for him. But who is? Lurton? Maybe even he doesn’t know where Cally is. She might have run out on him. Gone to the Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite and joined the army of girls there, under an assumed name. With relish, Myra pondered that, picturing her former husband’s mistress as one of Thisbe’s creatures, sexless and mechanical and automatic. Which will it be, Cally? One, two, three or four? Only, the choice isn’t yours. It’s theirs. Every time. Myra laughed. It’s where you ought to be, Cally, she thought.

For the rest of your life, for the next two hundred years.

“Please forgive the interruption,” Myra said to the young couple seated opposite her. “And do go on.”

“Well,” the girl Rachael said awkwardly, “Art and I felt that—we thought over the abortion and we just don’t want to do it. I don’t know why, Mrs. Sands. I know we should. But we can’t.”

There was silence, then.

“I don’t see what you came to me for,” Myra said. “If you’ve made up your minds against it already. Obviously, from a practical standpoint you should go through with it; you’re probably frightened . . . after all, you are very young. But I’m not trying to talk you into it. A decision of this sort has to be your own.”

In a low voice Art said, “We’re not scared, Mrs. Sands. That’s not it. We—well, we’d like to have the baby. That’s all.”

Myra Sands did not know what to say. She had never, in her practice, run into anything quite like this; it baffled her.

She could see already that this was going to be a bad day.

Between this and Tito’s phone call—it was too much. And so early. It was not yet even nine a.m.

In the basement of Pethel Jiff‘scuttler Sales & Service, the repairman Rick Erickson prepared, for the second day in a row, to enter the defective ‘scuttler of Dr. Lurton Sands, Jr. He still had not found what he was searching for.

However, he did not intend to give up. He felt, on an intuitive level, that he was very close. It would not be long now.

From behind him a voice said, “What are you doing, Rick?”

Startled, Erickson jumped, glanced around. At the door of the repair department stood his employer, Darius Pethel, heavy-set in the wrinkled dark-brown old-fashioned /i>jerry -type wool suit which he customarily wore.

“Listen,” Erickson said. “This is Dr. Sands’ ‘scuttler. You can laugh, but I think he’s got his mistress in here, somewhere.”

“What?” Pethel laughed.

“I mean it. I don’t think she’s dead, even though I talked to Sands long enough to know he could do it if he felt it was necessary—he’s that kind of guy. Anyhow nobody’s found her, even Mrs. Sands. Naturally they can’t find her, because Lurton’s got his ‘scuttler in here with us, out of sight. He knows it’s here, but they don’t. And he doesn’t want it back, no matter what he says; he wants it stuck down here, right in this basement.”

Staring at him Pethel said, “Great fud. Is this what you’ve been doing on my time? Working out detective theories?”

Erickson said, “This is important! Even if it doesn’t mean any money for you. Hell, maybe it does; if I’m lucky and find her, maybe you can sell her back to Mrs. Sands.”

After a pause Darius Pethel shrugged in a philosophical way. “Okay. So look. If you do find her?”

Beside Pethel the salesman of the firm, Stuart Hadley, appeared. He said breezily, “What’s up, Dar?” As always cheerful and interested.

“Rick’s searching for Dr. Sands’ mistress.” Pethel said. He jerked his thumb at the ‘scuttler.

“Is she pretty?” Hadley asked. “Well started?” He looked hungry.

“You’ve seen her pics in the homeopapes,” Pethel said. “She’s cute. Otherwise why do you suppose the doctor risked his marriage, if she wasn’t something exceptional? Come on, Hadley; I need you upstairs on the floor. We can’t all three be down here—someone’ll walk away with the register.” He started up the stairs.

“And she’s in there?” Hadley said, looking puzzled as he bent to peer into the ‘scuttler. “I don’t see her, Dar.”

Darius Pethel guffawed. “Neither do I. Neither does Rick, but he’s still searching—and on my time, goddam it! Listen, Rick; if you find her she’s my mistress, because you’re on my time, working for me.”

All three of them laughed at that.

“Okay,” Rick agreed, on his hands and knees, scraping the surface of the ‘scuttler tube with the blade of a screwdriver. “You can laugh and I admit it’s funny. But I’m not stopping. Obviously, the rent isn’t visible; if it was, Doc Sands wouldn’t have dared leave it here. He may think I’m dumb, but not that dumb—he’s got it concealed and real well.”

“‘Rent,’” Pethel echoed. He frowned, startling back a few steps down the stairs and into the basement once more. “You mean like Henry Ellis found, years ago? That rupture in the tube-wall that led to ancient Israel?”

“Israel is right,” Rick said briefly, as he scraped. His keen, thoroughly-trained eye saw all at once in the surface near at hand a slight irregularity, a distortion. Leaning forward, he reached out his hand . . .

His groping fingers passed through the wall of the tube and disappeared.

“Jesus,” Rick said. He raised his invisible fingers, felt nothing at first, and then touched the upper edge of the rent. “I found it,” he said. He looked around, but Pethel had gone. “Darius!” he yelled, but there was no answer. “Damn him!” he said in fury to Hadley.

“You found what?” Hadley asked, starting cautiously into the tube. “You mean you found the Vale woman? Cally Vale?”

Headfirst, Rick Erickson crept into the rent.

He sprawled, snatching for support; falling, he struck hard ground and cursed. Opening his eyes, he saw, above, a pale blue sky with a few meager clouds. And, around him, a meadow. Bees, or what looked something more or less like bees, buzzed in tall-stemmed white flowers as large as saucers. The air smelled of sweetness, as if the flowers had impregnated the atmosphere itself.

I’m there, he said to himself. I got through; this is where Doc Sands hid his mistress to keep her from testifying for Mrs. Sands at the trial or hearing or whatever it’s called. He stood up, cautiously. Behind him he made out a hazy shimmer: the nexus with the tube of the Jiffi−scuttler back in the store’s basement in Kansas City. I want to keep my bearings, he said to himself warily. If I get lost, I may not be able to get back again and that might be bad.

Where is this? he asked himself. Must work that out—now.

Gravity like Earth’s. Must be Earth, then, he decided. Long time ago? Long time in the future?

Think what this is worth; the hell with the man’s mistress, the hell with him and his personal problems—that’s nothing. He looked wildly around for some sign of habitation, for something animal-like, or human; something to tell him what epoch this was, past or future, Saber-tooth tiger, maybe. Or trilobite. No, too late for the trilobite already; look at those bees. This is the break Terran Development has been trying to uncover for thirty years now, he said to himself.

And the rat that found it used it for his own sneaky goings-on, as a place merely to hide his doxie. What a world! Erickson began slowly to walk, step by step . . .

Far off, a figure moved.

Shading his eyes against the glare of the sky, Rick−Erickson tried to make out what it was.

Primitive man? Cro−Magnon or some such thing? Big-domed inhabitant of the future, perhaps?

He squinted—it was a woman; he could tell by her hair. She wore slacks and she was running toward him. Cally, he thought. Doc Sands’ mistress, hurrying toward me. Must think I’m Sands.

In panic, he halted; what’ll I do? He wondered. Maybe I better go back, think this out. He started to turn in the direction he had come.

Out of the corner of his eye he saw the girl’s arm come up swiftly.

No, he thought. Don’t.

He stumbled as he snatched at the hazy, small loop which connected the two environments, entrance to the ‘scuttler tube.

The red glow of an aimed laser-beam passed over his head.

You missed me, he thought in terror. But—he clawed! for the entrance, found it, began to struggle back through. But next time. Next time!

“Stop,” he shouted at her without looking at heir. His voice echoed in the bee-zooming plain of flowers.

The second laser-beam caught him in the back.

He put his hand out, saw it pass through the haze and disappear beyond. It was safe, but he was not. She had killed him; it was too late, now, too late to get away from her. Why didn’t she wait? he asked himself. Find out who I was? Must have been afraid.

Again the laser-beam nicked. It touched the back of his head and that was that. There was no returning for him, no reentry into the safety of the tube.

Rick Erickson was dead.

Standing on the far side, in the tube of Dr. Sands’ Jiffi−scuttler, Stuart Hadley waited nervously, then saw Rick Erickson’s fingers jerk through the wall near the floor; the fingers writhed, and Hadley stooped down and grabbed Erickson by the wrist. Trying to get back, he realized, and pulled Erickson by the arm with all his strength. It was a corpse that he drew into the tube beside him.

Horrified, Hadley rose unsteadily to his feet; he saw the two clean holes and knew that Erickson had been killed with a laser rifle, probably from a distance. Stumbling down the tube, Hadley reached the controls of the ‘scuttler and cut the power off; the shimmer of the entrance hoop at once vanished, and he knew or hoped—that now they, whoever they were who had murdered Rick Erickson, could not follow him through.

“Pethel!” he shouted. “Come down here!” He ran to Erickson’s work bench and the intercom. “Mr. Pethel,” he said, “come back down here to the basement right away. Erickson’s dead.”

The next he knew, Darius Pethel stood beside him, examining the body of the repairman. “He must have found it,” Pethel muttered, ashen-faced and trembling. “Well, he got paid for his nosiness; he sure got paid.”

“We better get the police,” Hadley said.

“Yes.” Pethel nodded vacantly. “Of course. I see you turned it off. Good thing. We better leave it strictly alone. The poor guy, the poor goddam guy; look at what he got for being smart enough to figure it all out. Look, he’s got something in his hand.” He bent down, opening Erickson’s fingers.

The dead hand held a wad of grass.

“No org-trans operation can help him, either,” Pethel said. “Because the beam caught him in the head. Got his brain. Too bad.” He glanced at Stuart Hadley. “Anyhow the best org-trans surgeon is Sands and he isn’t going to do anything to help Erickson. You can make book on that.”

“A place where there’s grass,” Hadley murmured, touching the contents of the dead man’s hand.

“Where can it be? Not on Earth. Not now, anyway.”

“Must be the past,” Pethel said. “So we’ve got time-travel. Isn’t it great?” His face twisted with grief. “Terrific beginning, one good man dead. How many left to go? Imagine a guy’s reputation meaning that much to him, that he’d let this happen. Or maybe Sands doesn’t know; maybe she was just given the laser gun to protect herself. In case his wife’s private cops got to her. And anyhow, we don’t know for sure if she did it; it could have been someone else entirely, not Cally Vale at all. What do we know about it? All we know is that Erickson is dead. And there was something basically wrong with the theory he was going on.”

“You can give Sands the benefit of the doubt, if you want,” Hadley said, “but I’m not going to.” He stood up, then, taking a deep shuddering breath. “Can we get the police, now? You call them; I can’t talk well enough to. You do it, Pethel, okay?”

Unsteadily, Darius Pethel moved toward the phone on Erickson’s work bench, his hand extended gropingly, as if his perception of touch had begun to disintegrate. He picked up the receiver, and then he turned to Stuart Hadley and said, “Wait. This is a mistake. You know who we’ve got to call? The factory. We have to tell Terran Development about this; it’s what they’re after. They come first.”

Hadley, staring at him, said, “I—don’t agree. This is more important than what you think or I think, more important than Sands and Cally Vale, any of us.” Dar Pethel began to dial. “Even if one of us is dead. That still doesn’t matter. You know what I’m thinking about? Emigration. You saw the grass in Erickson’s hand. You know what it means. It means the hell with that girl on the far side, or whoever it is over there who shot Erickson. It means the hell with any of us and all of us, our sentiments and opinions.”

He gestured. “All our lives put together.”

Dimly, Stuart Hadley understood. Or thought he did. “But she’ll probably kill the next person who . . .”

“Let TD worry about that,” Pethel said savagely. “That’s their problem. They’ve got company police, armed guards they use for patrol purposes; let them send them over, first.” His voice was low and harsh. “Let them lose a few men, so what. The lives of millions of people are involved in this, now. You get that, Hadley? Do you?”

“Y-yes,” Hadley said, nodding.

“Anyhow,” Pethel said, more calmly, now, “it’s legitimately within the jurisdiction of TD because it look place within one of their ‘scuttlers. Call it an accident; think of it that way. Unavoidable and awful. Between an entrance and an exit hoop. Naturally the company has to know.” He turned his back to Hadley, then, concentrating on the vidphone, calling Leon Turpin, the chief of TD.

“I think,” Salisbury Heim said to his presidential candidate James Briskin, “I have something cooking you won’t like. I’ve been talking to George Walt . . .”

At once Jim Briskin said, “No deal. Not with them. I know what they want and that’s out, Sal.”

“If you don’t do business with George Walt,” Heim said steadily, “I’m going to have to resign as your campaign manager. I just can’t take any more, not after that planet-wetting speech of yours. Things are breaking too badly for us as it is, we can’t take George Walt on in addition to everything else.”

“There’s something even worse,” Jim Briskin said, after a pause. “Which you haven’t heard. A wire came from Bruno Mini. He was delighted with my speech and he’s on his way here to—as he puts it—‘join forces with me’.“

Heim said, “But you can still . . .”

“Mini’s already spoken to homeopape reporters. So it’s too late to head him off media-wise. Sorry.”

“You’re going to lose.”

“Okay, I’ll have to lose.”

“What gets me,” Heim said bitterly, “what really gets me is that even if you did win the election you couldn’t have it all your way; one man just can’t alter things that much. The Golden Door Movements of Bliss satellite is going to remain; the bibs are going to remain; so are Nonovulid and the abort-consultants you can chip away a little here and there but not . . .”

He ceased, because Dorothy Gill had come up to Jim Briskin. “A phone call for you, Mr. Briskin. The gentleman says it’s urgent and he won’t be wasting your time. You don’t know him, he says, so he didn’t give his name.” She added, “He’s a Col. If that helps you identify him.”

“It doesn’t,” Jim said. “But I’ll talk to him anyhow.” Obviously, he was glad to break off the conversation with Sal; relief showed on his face. “Bring the phone here, Dotty.”

“Yes, Mr. Briskin.” She disappeared and presently was back, carrying the extension vidphone.

“Thanks.” Jim Briskin pressed the hold button, releasing it, and the vidscreen glowed. A face formed, swarthy and handsome, a keen-eyed man, well-dressed and evidently agitated. Who is he? Sal Heim asked himself. I know him. I’ve seen a pic of him somewhere.

Then he identified the man. It was the big-time N’York investigator who was working for Myra Sands; it was a man named Tito Cravelli, and he was a tough individual indeed. What did he want with Jim?

The image of Tito Cravelli said, “Mr. Briskin, I’d like to have lunch with you. In private. I have something to discuss with you, just you and me; it’s vitally important to you, I assure you.” He added, with a glance toward Sal Heim, “So vital I don’t want anybody else around.”

Maybe this is going to be an assassination attempt, Sal Heim thought. Someone, a fanatic from CLEAN, sent by Verne Engel and his crowd of nuts. “You better not go, Jim,” he said aloud.

“Probably not,” Jim said. “But I am anyhow.” To the image on the vidscreen he said, “What time and where?”

Tito Cravelli said, “There’s a little restaurant in the N’York slum area, in the five hundred block of Fifth Avenue; I always eat there when I’m in N’York—the food’s prepared by hand. It’s called Scotty’s Place. Will that be satisfactory? Say at one p.m., N’York time.”

“All right,” Jim Briskin agreed. “At Scotty’s Place at one o’clock. I’ve been there.” He added tartly, “They’re willing to serve Cols.”

“Everyone serves Cols,” Tito said, “when I’m along.” He broke the connection; the screen faded and died.

“I don’t like this,” Sal Heim said.

“We’re ruined anyhow,” Jim reminded him. “Didn’t you say, just a minute ago?” He smiled laconically. “I think the time has arrived for me to clutch at straws, Sal. Any straw I can reach. Even this.”

“What shall I tell George Walt? They’re waiting. I’m supposed to set up a visit by you to the satellite within twenty-four hours; that would be by six o’clock tonight.” Getting out his handkerchief, Sal Heim mopped his forehead. “After that . . .”

“After that,” Jim said, “they begin systematically campaigning against me.”

Sal nodded.

“You can tell George Walt,” Jim said, “that in my Chicago speech today I’m going to come out and advocate the shutting of the satellite. And if I’m elected . . .”

“They know already,” Sal Heim said. “There was a leak.”

“There’s always a leak . . .” Jim did not seem perturbed.

Reaching into his coat pocket, Sal brought out a sealed envelope. “Here’s my resignation.” He had been carrying it for some time.

Jim Briskin accepted the envelope; without opening it he put it in his coat-pouch. “I hope you’ll be watching my Chicago speech, Sal. It’s going to be an important one.” He grinned sorrowfully at his ex-campaign manager; his pain at this breakdown of their relationship showed in the deep lines of his face. The break had been long in coming; it had hung there in the atmosphere between them in their former discussions.

But Jim intended to go on anyhow. And do what had to be done.

As he flew by Jet’ab to Scotty’s Place, Jim Briskin thought: At least now I don’t have to come out for Lurton Sands; I don’t have to follow Sal’s advice any more on any topic because if he’s not my campaign manager he can’t tell me what to do. To some extent it was a relief. But on a deeper level Jim Briskin felt acutely unhappy. I’m going to have trouble getting along without Sal, he realized. I don’t want to get along without him.

But it was already done. Sal, with his wife Patricia, had gone on to his home in Cleveland, for a much-delayed rest. And Jim Briskin, with his speechwriter Phil Danville and his press secretary Dorothy Gill, was on his way in the opposite direction, toward downtown N’York, its tiny shops and restaurants and old, decaying apartment buildings, and all the microscopic, outdated business offices where peculiar and occult transactions continually took place. It was a world which intrigued Jim Briskin, but it was also a world he knew little about; he had been shielded from it most of his life.

Seated beside him, Phil Danville said, “He may come back, Jim. You know Sal when he gets overburdened; he blows up, falls into fragments. But after a week of lazing around . . .”

“Not this time,” Jim said. The split was too basic.

“By the way,” Dorothy said, “before he left, Sal told me who this man you’re meeting is. Sal recognized him; did he tell you? It’s Tito Cravelli, Sal says. You know, Myra Sands’ investigator.”

“No,” Jim said. “I didn’t know.” Sal had said nothing to him; the period in which Sal Heim gave him the benefit of his experience was over, had ended there on the spot.

At Republican−Liberal campaign headquarters in N’York he stopped briefly to let off Phil Danville and Dorothy Grill, and then he went on, alone, to meet with Tito Cravelli at Scotty’s Place.

Cravelli, looking nervous and keyed-up, was already in a booth in the rear of the restaurant, waiting for him, when he arrived.

“Thanks, Mr. Briskin,” Tito Cravelli said, as Jim seated himself across from him. Hurriedly,

Cravelli sipped what remained of his cup of coffee. “This won’t take long. What I want for my information is a great deal. I want a promise from you that when you’re elected—and you will be, because of this—you’ll bring me in at cabinet rank.” He was silent, then.

“Good god,” Jim said mildly. “Is that all you want?”

“I’m entitled to it,” Cravelli said. “For getting this information to you. I came across it because I have someone working for me in . . .” He broke off abruptly. “I want the post of Attorney General; I think I can handle the job . . . I think I’d be a good Attorney General. If I’m not, you can fire me. But you have to let me in for a chance at it.”

“Tell me what your information is. I can’t make that promise until I hear it.”

Cravelli hesitated. “Once I tell you—but you’re honest, Briskin. Everyone knows that. There’s a way you can get rid of the bibs. You can bring them back to activity, full activity.”

“Where?”

“Not here,” Cravelli said. “Obviously. Not on Earth. The man I have working for me who picked this up is an employee of Terran Development. What does that suggest to you?”

After a pause Jim Briskin said, “They’ve made a breakthrough.”

“A little firm has. A retailer in Kansas City, repairing a defective Jiffi−scuttler. They did it—or rather found it. Discovered it. The ‘scuttler’s at TD, now, being gone over by factory engineers. It was moved east two hours ago; they acted immediately, as soon as the retailer contacted them. They knew what it meant.” He added, “Just as you and I do, and my man working for them.”

“Where’s the break-through to? What time period?”

“No time period, evidently. The conversion seems to have taken place in spacial terms, as near as they can determine. A planet with about the same mass as Earth, similar atmosphere, welldeveloped fauna and flora, but not Earth—they managed to snap a sky-chart, get a stellar reading. Within another few hours they’ll probably have plotted lit exactly, know which star-system it lies in. Apparently it’s a long, long way from here. Too far for direct deeps-ace ships to probe—at least for some time to come. This break-through, this direct shorted-out route, will have to be utilized for at least the next few decades.”

The waitress, came for Jim’s order.

“Perkin’s Syn—Cof,” he murmured absently.

The waitress departed.

“Cally Gale’s there,” Tito Cravelli said.

“What!”

“Doctor put her across. That’s why my man got in touch with me; as you may know, I’ve been retained to search for Cally, trying to produce her on demand for the trial. It’s a mess; she lasered an employee of this Kansas City retailer, its one and only tried and true ‘scuttler repairman. He had gone across, exploring. Too bad for him. But in the great scheme of all things . . .”

“Yes,” Jim Briskin agreed. Cravelli was right; it was small cost indeed. With so many millions of lives—and, potentially, billions—involved.

“Naturally TD has declared this top-secret. They’ve thrown up an enormous security screen; I was lucky to get hold of the poop at all. If I hadn’t already had a man in there . . .” Cravelli gestured.

“I’ll name you to the cabinet,” Jim Briskin said. “As Attorney General. The arrangement doesn’t please me, but I think it’s in order.” It’s worth it, he said to himself. A hundred times over. To me and to everyone else on Earth, bibs and non-bibs alike. To all of us.

Sagging with relief and exultation,, Tito Cravelli burbled, “Wow. I can’t believe it; this is great!”

He held out his hand, but Jim ignored it; he had too much else on his mind at the moment to want to congratulate Tito Cravelli.

Jim thought, Sal Heim got out a little too soon. He should have stuck around. So much for Sal’s political intuition; at the crucial moment it had failed to materialize for him.

Seated in her office, abort-consultant Myra Sands once more leafed through Tito’s brief report.

But already, outside her window, a news machine for one of the major homeopapes was screeching out the news that Cally Vale had been found; it had been made public by the police.

I didn’t think you could do it, Tito, Myra said to herself. Well, I was wrong. You were worth your fee, large as it is.

It will be quite a trial, she said to herself with relish.

From a nearby office, probably the brokerage firm next door, the amplified sound of a man’s voice rose up and then was turned down to a more reasonable level. Someone had tuned in the TV, was watching the Republican−Liberal presidential candidate giving his latest speech.

Perhaps I should listen, too, she decided, and reached to turn on the TV set at her desk.

The set warmed, and there, on the screen, appeared the dark, intense features of Jim Briskin. She swiveled her chair toward the set and momentarily put aside Tito’s report. After all, anything James Briskin said had become important; he might easily be their next president.

“. . . an initial action on my part,” Briskin was saying, “and one which many may disapprove of, but one dear to my heart, will be to initiate legal action against the so-called Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite. I’ve thought about this topic for some time; this is not a snap decision on my part. But, much more vital than that, I think we will see the Golden Door satellite become thoroughly obsolete. That would be best of all. The role of sexuality in our society could return to its biological norm: as a means to childbirth rather than an end in itself.”

Oh, really? Myra thought archly. Exactly how?

“I am about to give you a piece of news which none of you have heard,” Briskin continued. “It will make a vast difference in all our lives . . . so great, in fact, that no one could possibly foresee its full extent at this time, A new possibility for emigration is about to open up at last. At Terran Development . . .”

On Myra’s desk the vidphone rang. Cursing in irritation, she turned down the sound of the television set and took the receiver from its support. “This is Mrs. Sands,” she said. “Could you please call back in a few moments, thank you? I’m extremely busy right now.”

It was the dark-haired boy, Art Chaffy. “We were just wondering what you’d decided,” he mumbled apologetically. But he did not ring off. “It means a lot to us, Mrs. Sands.”

“I know it does, Art,” Myra Sands said, “but if you’ll just give me a few more minutes, possibly half an hour . . .” She strained to hear what James Briskin was saying on the television; almost, she could make out the low murmur of words. What was his new news? Where were they going to emigrate to? A virgin environment? Well, obviously; it would have to be. But precisely where is it? Myra wondered. Are you about to pull this virgin world out of your sleeve, Mr. Briskin?

Because if you are, I would like to see it done; that would be worth watching.

“Okay,” Art Chaffy said. “I’ll call you later, Mrs. Sands. And I’m sorry to pester you.” He rang off, then.

“You ought to be listening to Briskin’s speech,” Myra murmured aloud as she swung her chair back to face the television set; bending, she turned the audio knob and the sound of Briskin’s voice rose once more to clear audibility. You of all people, she said to herself.

“. . . and according to reports reaching me,” Briskin said slowly and gravely, “it has an atmosphere nearly identical to that of earth, and a similar mass as well.”

Good grief, Myra Sands said to herself. If that’s the case then I’m out of a job. Her heart labored painfully. No one would need abort brokers any more. But frankly I’m just as glad, she decided.

It’s a task I’d like to see end—forever.

Hands pressed together tautly, she listened to the remainder of Jim Briskin’s momentous Chicago speech.

My god, she thought. This is a piece of history being made, this discovery. If it’s true. If this isn’t just a campaign stunt.

Somewhere inside her she knew that it was true. Because Jim Briskin was not the kind of person who would make this up.

At the Oakland, California, branch of the U.S. Government Department of Special Public Welfare, Herbert Lackmore also sat listening to presidential candidate Jim Briskin’s Chicago speech, being carried on all channels of the TV as it was beamed from the R−L satellite above.

He’ll be elected now, Lackmore realized. We’ll have a Col president at last, just what I was afraid of.

And, if what he’s saying is so, this business about a new possibility of emigration to an untouched world with fauna and flora like Earth’s, it means the bibs will be awakened. In fact, he realized with a thrill of fright, it means there won’t be any more bibs. At all.

That would mean that Herb Lackmore’s job would come to an end. And right away.

Because of him, Lackmore said to himself, I’m going to be out of work; I’ll be in the same spot as all the Cols who come by here in a steady stream, day in day out—I’ll be like some nineteen-yearold Mexican or Puerto Rican or Negro kid, without prospects or hope. All I’ve established over the years—wiped out by this. Completely.

With shaking fingers, Herb Lackmore opened the local phone book and turned the pages.

It was time to get hold of—and join—the organization of Verne Engel’s which called itself CLEAN. Because CLEAN would not sit idly by and let this happen, not if CLEAN believed as Herb Lackmore did.

Now was the time for CLEAN to do something. And not necessarily of a non-violent nature; it was too late for non-violence to work. Something more was required, now. Much more. The situation had taken a dreadful turn and it would have to be rectified, by direct and quick action.

And if they won’t do it, Lackmore said to himself, I will. I’m not afraid to; I know it has to be done.

On the TV screen Jim Briskin’s face was stern as he said. “. . . will provide a natural outlet for the biological pressures at work on everyone in our society. We will be free at last to . . .”

“You know what this means?” George of George Walt said to his brother Walt.

“I know,” Walt answered. “It means that nurf Sal Heim got nothing for us, nothing at all. You watch Briskin; I’m going to call Verne Engel and make some kind of arrangements. Him we can work with.”

“Okay,” George said, nodding their shared head. He kept his eye on the TV screen, while his brother dialed the vidphone.

“All that gabble with Sal Heim,” Walt grumbled, and then became silent as his brother stuck him with his elbow, signaling that he wanted to listen to the Chicago speech. “Sorry,” Walt said, turning his eye to the vidscreen of the phone.

At the door of their office Thisbe Olt appeared, wearing a fawnskin gown with alternating stripes of magnifying transparency. “Mr. Heim is back,” she informed them. “To see you. He looks— dejected.”

“We’ve got no business to conduct with Sal Heim,” George said, with anger.

“Tell him to go back to Earth,” Walt added. “And from now on the satellite is closed to him; he can’t visit any of our girls—at any price. Let him die a miserable, lingering death of frustration; it’ll serve him right.”

George reminded him acidly, “Heim won’t need us any more, if Briskin is telling the truth.”

“He is,” Walt said. “He’s too simple a horse’s ass to lie; Briskin doesn’t have the ability.” His call had been put through on the private circuit, now. On the vidscreen appeared the miniature image of one of Verne Engel’s gaudily-uniformed personal praetorian flunkies, the green and silver outfit of the CLEAN people. “Let me talk directly to Verne,” Walt said, making use of their common mouth just as George was about to address a few more remarks to Thisbe. “Tell him this is Walt, on the satellite.”

“Run along,” George said to Thisbe, when Walt had finished. “We’re busy.”

Thisbe eyed him momentarily and then shut the office door after her.

On the screen Verne Engel’s pinched, wabble-like face materialized. “I see you—at least half of you—are following Briskin’s rabble-rousing,” Engel said. “How did you decide which half was to call me and which half was to listen to the Col?” Engel’s distorted features twisted in a leer of derision.

“Watch it—that’s enough,” George Walt retorted simultaneously.

“Sorry. I don’t mean to offend you,” Engel said, but his expression remained unchanged. “Well, what can I do for you? Please make it brief; I’d like to follow Briskin’s harangue too.”

“You’re going to require help,” Walt said to Engel. “If you’re going to stop Briskin now; this speech will put him across, and I don’t think even concerted transmissions from our satellite—as we discussed—will be sufficient. It’s just too damn clever the speech he’s making. Isn’t it, George?”

“It certainly is,” George said, eye fixed on the TV screen. “And getting better each second as he goes along. He’s barely getting; started; it’s a genuine spellbinder. Whacking fine.”

His eye on the vidscreen, Walt continued, “You heard Briskin come out against us; you must have heard that part—everyone else in the country certainly did. Planet-wetting with Bruno Mini isn’t enough, he’s also got to take us on. Big plans for a Col, but evidently he and his advisors feel he can handle it. We’ll see. What do you plan to do, Engel? At this very crucial point?”

“I’ve got plans, I’ve got plans,” Engel assured him.

“Still no-violence stuff?”

There was no audible answer, but Engel’s face contorted oddly.

“Come up here to the Golden Door,” Walt said, “and let’s talk. I think my brother and I can see our way clear to make a donation to CLEAN, say in the neighborhood of ten or eleven mil. Would that help? You ought to be able to buy what you need with money like that.”

Engel, white with shock, stammered, “S-sure, George or Walt, whichever you are.”

“Get up here as soon as you can, then,” Walt instructed him, and rang off. “I think he’ll do it for us,” he said to his brother.

“A gorp like that can’t handle anything;,” George said sourly.

“Then for pop’s sake, what do we do?” Walt demanded.

“We do what we can. We help out Engel, we prompt him, shove him if necessary. But we don’t pin our hopes on him, at least not entirely. We go ahead with something on our own, just to be certain. And we have to be certain; this is too serious. That Col actually means to shut us down.”

Both their eyes, now, turned toward the TV screen, and both George and Walt sat back in their special wide couch to listen to the speech.

In the luxurious apartment which he maintained in Reno, Dr. Lurton Sands sat raptly listening to the television set, the Col candidate James Briskin delivering his Chicago speech. He knew what it meant. There was only one place that Briskin could have happened across a ‘lush, virgin world’. Obviously Cally had been found.

Going to his desk drawer, Lurton Sands got out the small laser pistol which he kept there and thrust it into his coat pocket. I’m amazed he’d do it, Sands thought. Capitalize off my problems —evidently I misjudged him.

Now so many lives which I could have saved will be forfeited, Sands realized. Due to this. And Briskin is responsible . . . he’s taken the healing power out of my hands, darkened the force working for the good of man.

At the vidphone Sands dialed the local jet’ab company. “I want an “ab to Chicago. As soon as possible.” He gave his address, then hurried from his apartment to the elevator. Those that are hounding Cally and me to our deaths, he thought, Myra and her detectives and the homeopapes . . . now they’ve been joined by Jim Briskin. How could he align himself with them?

Haven’t I made clear to everyone what I can do in the service of human need? Briskin must be aware; this ain’t be merely ignorance on his part.

Frantically Sands thought. Could it possibly be that Briskin wants the sick to die? All those waiting for me, needing my help . . . help which no one else, after I’ve been pushed to my death, can possibly provide.

Touching the laser pistol in his pocket, Sands said aloud, glumly, “It certainly is easy to be mistaken about another person.” They can take you in so easily, he thought. Deliberately mislead you. Yes, deliberately!

The jet’ab swept up to the curb and slid open its door.

When he had finished his speech Jim Briskin sat back and knew that this time he had done, at last, a damn good job. It had been the best speech of his political career, in some respects the only really decent one.

And now what? he asked himself. Sal is gone, and along with him Patricia. I’ve offended the powerful and immensely wealthy unicephalic brothers George Walt, not to mention Thisbe herself . . . and Terran Development, which is no small potatoes, will be furious that its breakthrough has been made public. But none of this matters. Nor does the fact that I’m now committed to naming a well-known private operator as my Attorney General; even that isn’t important. My job was to make that speech as soon as Tito Cavelli brought me that information.

And— that’s exactly what I did. To the letter. No matter what the consequences.

Coming up to him, Phil Danville slapped him warmly on the back. “A hell of a good fuss, Jim. You really outdid yourself.”

“Thanks, Phil,” Jim Briskin murmured. He felt tired. He nodded to the TV camera men and then, with Phil Danville, walked over to join the knot of party brass waiting at the rear of the studio.

“I need a drink,” Jim said to them as several of them extended their hands, wanting to shake with him. “After that.” I wonder what the opposition will do now, he said to himself. What can Bill Schwarz say? Nothing, actually. I’ve taken the lid off the whole thing, and there’s no putting it back. Now that everyone knows there’s a place we can emigrate to, the rush will be on. By the multitudes. The warehouses will be emptied, thank god. As they should have been long ago.

I wish I had known about this, he thought abruptly, before I began publicly advocating Bruno Mini’s planet-wetting technique. I could have avoided that—and the break with Sal as well.

But anyhow, he said to himself, I’ll be elected.

Dorothy Gill said quietly to him, “Jim, I think you’re in.”

“I know he is,” Phil Danville agreed, grinning with pure delight. “How about it, Dotty? It’s not like it was a little while ago. How’d you get hold of that info about TD, Jim? It must have cost you . . .”

“It did,” Jim Briskin said shortly. “It cost me too much. But I’d pay it two times over.”

“Now for the drink,” Phil said. “There’s a bar around the corner; I noticed it when we were coming in here. Let’s go.” He started for the door and Jim Briskin followed, hands deep in his overcoat pockets.

The sidewalk, he discovered, was crowded with people, a mob which waved at him, cheered him; he waved back, noticing that many of them were Whites as well as Cols. A good sign, he reflected as his party moved step by step through the dense mass of people, uniformed Chicago city police clearing a path for them to the bar which Phil Danville had picked out.

From the crowd a red-headed girl, very small, wearing dazzling wubfur lounging pajamas, the kind fashionable with the girls on the Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite, came hurrying, gliding and ducking toward him breathlessly. “Mr. Briskin . . .”

He paused unwillingly, wondering who she was; and what she wanted. One of Thisbe Olt’s girls, evidently. “Yes,” he said, and smiled at her.

“Mr. Briskin,” the little red-haired girl gasped, “there’s a rume going around the satellite—George Walt’s doing something with Verne Engel, the man from CLEAN.” She caught hold of him anxiously by the arm, stopping him. “They’re going to assassinate you or something. Please be careful.” Her face was stark with alarm.

“What’s your name?” Jim asked.

“Sparky Rivers. I—work there, Mr. Briskin.”

“Thanks, Sparky,” he said. “I’ll remember you. Maybe sometime I can give you a cabinet post.” He continued to smile at her, but she did not smile back. I’m just joking,” he said. “Don’t be downcast.”

“I think they’re going to kill you,” Sparky said.

“Maybe so.” He shrugged. It was certainly possible. He leaned forward, briefly, and kissed her on the forehead. Take care of yourself, too,” he said, and then walked away with Phil Danville and Dorothy Gill.

After a time Phil said, “What are you going to do, Jim?”

“Nothing. What can I do? Wait, I guess. Get my drink.”

“You’ll have to protect yourself,” Dorothy Gill said. If anything happens to you—what’ll we do then? The rest of us;.”

Jim Briskin said, “Emigration will still exist, even without me. You can still wake the sleepers. As it says in Bach’s Cantata 140, ‘Wachet auf’. Sleepers, awake. That’ll have to be your watchword, from now on.”

“Here’s the bar,” Phil Danville said. Ahead of them, a Chicago policeman held the door open for them, and they entered one at a time.

“It was darn nice of that girl to warn me,” Jim Briskin said.

A man’s voice, close to him, said, “Mr. Briskin? I’m Lurton Sands, Jr. Perhaps you’ve been reading about me in the homeopapes, lately.”

“Oh, yes,” Jim said, surprised to see him; he held out his hand in greeting. I’m glad to meet you, Dr. Sands, I want to . . .”

“May I talk, please?” Sands said. “I have something to say to you. Because of you, my life and the humanitarian work of two decades is wrecked. Don’t answer; I’m not going to get into an argument with you. I’m simply telling you, so you’ll understand why.” Sands reached into his coat pocket. Now he held a laser pistol, pointed directly at Jim Briskin’s chest. “I don’t quite understand what it is about my dedication to the sick that offended you and made you turn against me, but everybody else has, so why not you? After all, Mr. Briskin, what better life-task could you set yourself than wrecking mine?” He squeezed the trigger of the pistol The pistol did not fire, and Lurton Sands stared down at it in disbelief. “Myra, my wife.” He sounded almost apologetic. “She removed the energy cartridge, obviously. Evidently, she thought I’d try to use it on her.” He tossed the pistol away.

After a pause Jim Briskin said huskily, “Well, now what, Doctor?”

“Nothing, Briskin. Nothing. If I had had more time I would have checked the gun out, but I had to hurry to get here before you left. That was quite a heroic speech you made; it’ll certainly give most people the impression that you’re seeking to alleviate man’s problems . . . although of course you and I know better. By the way—you do realize you won’t be able to awaken all the bibs; you can’t fulfill that promise because some are dead. I’m responsible for that. Roughly four hundred of them.”

Jim Briskin stared at him.

“That’s right,” Sands said. “I’ve had access to Department of Special Public Welfare warehouses. Do you know what that means? Every organ I’ve taken has created a dead human—when the time comes for them to be revived, whenever that may be. But I suppose the trump has to be played sooner or later. doesn’t it?”

“You’d do that?” Jim Briskin said.

“I did that,” Sands corrected. “But remember this: I killed only potentially. Whereas, in exchange, I saved someone right now, someone conscious and alive in the present someone completely dependent on my skill.”

Two Chicago policemen shoved their way up to him; Dr. Sands jerked irritably away but they continued to hold onto him, pinning him between them.

Pale, Phil Danville said, “That—was almost it, Jim. Wasn’t it?” He deliberately stepped between Jim Briskin and Dr. Sands, shielding Briskin. “History revisited.”

“Yes,” Jim managed to say. He nodded, his mouth dry. Basically he felt resigned. If Lurton Sands did not manage to carry it off then, certainly someone else would, given time. It was just too easy. Weapons technology had improved too much in the last hundred years; everyone knew that, and now the assassin did not even have to be in his vicinity. Like an act of evil magic it could be done from a distance. And the instruments were cheap and available to virtually anyone— even, as history had shown, some ignorant, worthless smallfry, without friends, funds, or even a fanatical purpose, an overriding political cause.

This incident with Lurton Sands was a vile harbinger.

“Well,” Phil Danville said, and sighed, “I guess we have to go on. What do you want to drink?”

“A Black Russian,” Jim decided, after a pause. “Vodka and . . .”

“I know,” Phil interrupted. His face still ragged with fear and gloom, he made his way unsteadily over to the bar to order.

To Dotty, Jim said, “Even if they get me, I’ve done my job. I keep telling myself that over and over again, anyhow. I broke the news about TD’s break-through and that’s enough.”

“Do you actually mean that?” she demanded. “You’re that fatalistic about it, about your chances?”

She stared un-wincingly up into his face.

“Yes,” he said, finally. And well he might be.

I have a feeling, he thought to himself, that this is not the time a Negro is going to make it to the presidency.

His contact within CLEAN came via an individual named Dave DeWinter. DeWinter had joined the movement at its inception and had reported to Tito Cravelli throughout. Now, hurriedly,

DeWinter told his employer the most recent—and urgent—news.

“They’ll try it late tonight. The man actually doing it is not a member. His name is Herb Lackmore or Luckmore. and with the equipment they’re providing him he doesn’t need to be an accurate shot.” DeWinter added, “The equipment, what they call a boulder, was paid for by George Walt, those two mutants who own the Golden Door.”

Tito Cravelli said, “I see.” There goes my post as Attorney General, he said to himself. “Where can I find this Lackmore right now?”

“In his con apt in Oakland, California. Probably eating dinner; it’s about six, there.”

From the locked closet of his office, Tito Cravelli got a collapsible high-powered scope-sight laser rifle, he folded it up and stuffed it into his pocket, out of sight. Such a rifle was strictly illegal, but that hardly mattered right now; what Cravelli intended to do was against the law with any kind of weapon.

But it was already too late to get Lackmore or Luckmore or whatever his name was. By the time he reached the West Coast Lackmore would certainly be gone, on his way east to intercept Jim Briskin; their flights would cross, his and Lackmore’s. Better to locate Briskin and stick close to him, get Lackmore when he showed up. But Herb Lackmore would not have to show up, in the strict sense, not with the variety of weapon which the mutant brothers had provided him. He could be as far away as ten miles—and still reach Briskin.

George Walt will have to call him off, Cravelli decided. It’s the only sure way—and even that is merely relatively sure.

I’ll have to go to the satellite, he said to himself. Now, if I expect to accomplish anything at all.

The mutants George Walt would not be expecting him; they had no knowledge of his ties with Jim Briskin—or so he hoped. And also, he had three individuals working for him on the satellite, three of the girls. That gave him three separate places to stay—or hide—while he was up there.

Afterwards, after he took care of George Walt, it might well mean the difference in saving his life.

That, of course, would be if George Walt wouldn’t do business with him, if they chose to fight it out. In a fight, they would lose; Tito Cravelli was a crack shot. And in addition the initiative would be with him.

Where was the Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite right now? Getting the evening homeopape, he turned to the entertainment page. If it was, say, over India, he had no chance; he would not be able to reach the brothers in time.

The Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite, according to the time-schedule shown in the paper, was right now over Utah. By jet’ab he could reach it within three quarters of an hour.

That was soon enough.

“Thanks a lot,” he said to Dave De Winter, who stood awkwardly in the middle of the office, wearing his splendid green and silver CLEAN uniform. “You trot on back to Engel I’ll keep in touch with you.” He left the office on a dead run, then, racing down the stairs to the ground floor.

Presently, he was on his way to the satellite.

When the jet’ab had landed at the field, Cravelli hurried down the ramp, purchased a ticket from the nude, golden-haired attendant, and then rushed through gate five, searching for Francy’s door.

705, it was—or so he recalled, but under so much tension he felt rattled. With five thousand doors spread out in corridor after corridor—and all around him, on every side, the animated pics of the girls twisted and chirped, trying to snare his attention and entice him to the joys inside.

I’ll have to consult the satellite’s directory, he decided. That would waste precious time, but what alternative did he have? Feverishly, he loped down the corridor until he arrived at the immensely extensive, cross-indexed, illuminated directory board, with all its names winking on and off as rooms emptied and refilled, as customers hurried in and out.

It was 507, and it was empty of customers.

When he opened the door Francy said, “Hello!” and sat up, then, blinking in surprise to see him.

“Mr. Cravelli,” she said uncertainly. “Is everything all right?” She slid from the bed, wearing a pale smock of some cheap thin material, and came hesitantly up to him, her body bare and smooth. “What can I do for you? Are you here for . . .”

“Not for pleasure,” Tito Cravelli informed her. “Button up your damn smock and listen to me. Is there any way you can get George Walt up here?”

Fancy pondered. “They never visit a crib, normally. I . . .”

“Suppose there was trouble. A customer refusing to pay.”

“No. A bouncer would show up then. But George Walt would come here if they thought the FBI or some other police agency had moved in here and was officially arresting us girls.” She pointed to an obscure button on the wall. “For such an emergency. They have a regular neurosis about the police; they think it’s bound to come, sooner or later—they must have a guilty conscience about it. The button, connects to that great big office of theirs.”

“Ring the button,” Cravelli said, and got out his laser rifle seating himself on Francy’s bed, he began to assemble it.

Minutes passed.

Standing uneasily at the door, listening, Francy said “What’s going to happen in here Mr. Cravelli? I hope there’s no . . .”

“Be quiet,” he said sharply.

The door of the room opened.

The mutants George Walt stood in the entrance, one hand on the knob, the other three gripping short lengths of metal piping.

Tito Cravelli leveled the laser rifle and said, “My intention is not to kill both of you but merely one of you. That’ll leave the other with half a dead brain, one dead eye, and a deteriorating body attached to him. I don’t think you’d appreciate that. Can you threaten me with anything equally dreadful? I seriously doubt it.”

After a pause one of them—he did not know which—said, “What—do you want?” The face was twisting and livid, the two eyes, not in unison, staring, one of them at Tito, the other at his laser rifle.

“Come in and close the door,” Tito Cravelli said.

“Why?” George Walt demanded. “What’s this all about, anyhow?”

“Just come on in,” Tito said, and waited.

The mutants entered. The door shut after them and they stood facing him, still gripping the three lengths of metal piping. “This is George,” the head said presently. “Who are you? Let’s be reasonable; if you’re dissatisfied with the service you’ve received from this woman—no, can’t you see this is a strong-arm robbery?” the head interrupted itself as the other brother took control of the vocal apparatus. “He’s here to rob us; he brought that weapon with him, didn’t he?”

“You’re going to get in touch with Verne Engel,” Tito said. “And he’s going to get in touch with his gunsel, Herbert Lackmore. Together you’re going to call this Lackmore back in. We’ll do it from your office; obviously we can’t call from this woman’s crib.” To Francy he said, “You go ahead of them, lead the way. Start now, please. There’s no excess of time.” Within him his pyloric valve began to writhe in spasms; he gritted his teeth and for an instant shut his eyes.

A length of piping whistled past his head.

Tito Cravelli fired the laser rifle at George Walt. One of the two bodies sagged, hit in the shoulder; it was wounded but not dead. “You see?” Cravelli said. “It would be terrible for the one of you that survived.”

“Yes,” the head said, bobbing up and down in a grotesque pumpkin-like fit of nodding. “We’ll work with you, whoever you are. We’ll call Engel; we can get this all straightened out. Please.”

Both eyes, each fixed on a different spot, bulged in glazed fear. The right one, on the same side as the laser-wound, had become opaque with pain.

“Good enough,” Tito Cravelli said. He thought, I may be Attorney General yet. Herding them with his laser rifle, be moved George Walt toward the door.

The weapon which Herb Lackmore had been provided with contained a costly replica of the encephalic wave-pattern of James Briskin. He needed merely to place it within a few miles of Briskin, screw in the handle and then, with a switch, detonate it.

It was a mechanism, he decided, which supplied little, if any, personal satisfaction. However, at least it would do the job and that, in the long run, was all that counted. And certainly it insured his personal escape, or at least greatly aided it.

At this moment, nine o’clock at night, Jim Briskin sat upstairs in a room at the Galton Plaza Hotel, in Chicago, conferring with aides and idea-men; pickets of CLEAN, parading before the notably first class hotel, had seen him enter and had conveyed the word to Lackmore.

I’ll do it at exactly nine-fifteen, Lackmore decided. He sat in the back of a rented wheel, the mechanism assembled beside him; it was no larger than a football but rather heavy. It hummed faintly, off-key.

I wonder where the funds for this apparatus appeared from, he wondered. Because these items cost a hell of a lot, or so I’ve read.

He was, a few minutes later, just making the final preparatory adjustments when two dark, massive, upright shapes materialized along the nocturnal sidewalk close beside the wheel. The shapes appeared to be wearing green and silver uniforms which sparkled faintly, like moonlight.

Cautiously, with a near−Psionic sense of suspicions, Lackmore rolled down the wheel window.

“What do you want?” he asked the two CLEAN members.

“Get out,” one of them said brusquely.

“Why?” Lackmore froze, did not budge. Could not.

“There’s been an alteration of plans. Engel just now buzzed us on the portable seek-com. You’re to give that boulder back to us.”

“No,” Lackmore said. Obviously, the CLEAN movement had at the last moment sold out; he did not know exactly why, but there it was. The assassination would not take place as planned—that was all he knew, all he cared about. Rapidly, he began to screw the handle in.

“Engel says to forget it!” the other CLEAN man shouted. “Don’t you understand?”

“I understand,” Lackmore said, and groped for the detonating switch.

The door of his wheel popped open. One of the CLEAN men grabbed him by the collar, yanked him from the back seat and dragged him kicking and thrashing from the wheel and out onto the sidewalk. The other snatched up the boulder, the expensive weapon, from him and swiftly, expertly, unscrewed the detonating handle.

Lackmore bit and fought. He did not give up.

It did him no good. The CLEAN man with the boulder had already disappeared into the night darkness; along with the weapon he had vanished—the boulder, and all of Lackmore’s tireless, busy, brooding plans, had gone.

“I’ll kill you,” Lackmore panted futilely, struggling with the fat, powerful CLEAN man who had hold of him.

“You’ll kill nobody, fella,” the CLEAN man answered, and increased his pressure on Lackmore’s throat.

It was not an even fight; Herb Lackmore had no chance. He had sat at a government desk, stood idly behind a counter too many years.

Calmly, with clear enjoyment, the CLEAN man made mincemeat out of him.

For someone supposedly devoted to the cult of non-violence, it was amazing how good he was at it.

From the two mutants’ plush, Titan elk-beetle fuzz; carpeted office, Tito Cravelli vidphoned Jim Briskin at the Gallon Plaza Hotel in Chicago.

“Are you all right?” he inquired.

One of the Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite’s nurses was engaged in attempting futilely to bind up the injured brother with a dermofax pack; she worked silently, as Cravelli held the laser rifle and Francy stood by the office door with a pistol which Tito had located in the brothers’ desk.

“I’m all right,” Briskin said, puzzled. He evidently could see around Tito, past him to George Walt.

Tito said. “I’ve got a. snake by the tail here, and I can’t let go. You have any suggestions? I’ve prevented your assassination, but how the heck am I going to get out of here?” He was beginning to become really worried.

After meditating, Briskin said, “I could ask the Chicago police . . .”

“Niddy,” Cravelli said, in derision. “They wouldn’t come.” He knew that for a certainty. “They have no jurisdiction up here; that’s been tested countless times—this isn’t part of the United States, even, let alone Chicago.”

Briskin said, “All right. I can send some party volunteers up to help you. They’ll go where I say. We have a few who’ve clashed on the streets with Engel’s organization; they might know exactly what to do.”

“That’s more like it,” Cravelli said., relieved. But his stomach was still killing him; he could scarcely stand the pain and he wondered if there were any way he could obtain a glass of milk.

“The tension’s getting me down, he said. “And I haven’t had my dinner. They’ll have to get up here pretty soon, or frankly I’m going to fold up. I thought of taking George Walt off the satellite entirely, but I’m afraid I’d never get them to the launch field. We’d have to pass too many Golden Door employees on the way.”

“You’re directly over N’York now,” Jim Briskin said. “So it won’t take too long to get a few people there. How many do you want?”

“Certainly at least a hopper-load. Actually, all you can spare. You don’t want to lose your future Attorney General, do you?”

“Not especially.” Briskin seemed calm, but his dark eyes were bright. He plucked at his great handlebar mustache, then, pondering. “Maybe I’ll come along,” he decided.

“Why?”

“To make sure you get away.”

“It’s up to you,” Cravelli said. “But I don’t recommend it. Things are somewhat hot, up here. Do you know any girls at the satellite who could lead you through to George Walt’s office?”

“No,” Jim Briskin said. And then a peculiar expression appeared on his face. “Wait. I know one. She was down here in Chicago today but perhaps she’s gone back up again.”

“Probably has,” Cravelli said. “They flit back and forth like lightning bugs. Take a chance on it, anyhow. I’ll see you. And watch your step.” He rang off at that point.

As he started to board the big jet-bus, which was filled with R−L volunteers, Jim Briskin found himself facing two familiar figures.

“You can’t go to the satellite,” Sal Heim said, stopping him. Beside him Patricia stood somberly in her long coat, severing in the evening wind that drew in off the lakes. “It’s too dangerous . . . I know George Walt better than you do—remember? After all, I had you figured for a business deal with them; that was to be my contribution.”

Pat said, “If you go there, Jim, you’ll never come back. I know if. Stay here with me.” She caught hold of his arm, but he tugged loose.

“I have to go,” he told her. “My gunsel is there and I have to get him away; he’s done too much for me just to leave him there.”

“I’ll go instead of you,” Sal Heim said.

“Thanks.” It was a good offer, well meant. But—he had to repay Tito Cravelli for what he’d done; obviously he had to see that Tito got safely away from the Golden Door Moments of Bliss satellite. It was as simple as that. “The best I can offer you,” he said, “is the opportunity to ride along.” He meant it ironically.

“All right.” Sal said, nodding. “I’ll come with you.” To Pat he said, “but you stay down below here. If we get back, we should be showing up right away—or not at all. Come on, Jim.” He climbed the steps into the jet-bus, joining the others already there.

“Take care of yourself,” Pat said to Jim Briskin.

“What did you think of my speech?” he asked her.

“I was in the tub; I only heard part of it. But I think it was the best you ever made. Sal said so, too, and he heard it all. Now he knows he made a terrific mistake; he should have stuck with you.”

“Too bad he didn’t,” Jim said.

“You wouldn’t say something along the lines of “better late than . . .”

“Okay,” he said. “Better late than never.” Turning, he followed Sal Heim onto the jet-bus. He had said it, but it was not true. Too much had happened; too late was too late. He and Sal had split forever. And both of them knew it . . . or rather, feared it. And sought instinctively for a new rapprochement without having any idea how it could be done.

As the jet-bus whirled upward in brisk ascent, Sal leaned over and said, “You’ve accomplished a lot since I saw you last, Jim. I want to congratulate you. And I’m not being ironic. Hardly that.”

“Thanks,” Jim Briskin said, briefly.

“But you’ll never forgive me for handing you my resignation when I did, will you? Well, I can’t really blame you.” Sal was silent, then.

“You could have been Secretary of State,” Jim said.

Sal nodded. “But that’s the way the fifty yarrow stalks fall. Anyhow, I hope you win, Jim. I know you will, after that speech; that certainly was a masterpiece of promising everything to everybody—a billion gold chickens in a billion gold pots. Needless to say I think you’ll make a superb president. One we all can be proud of.” He grinned warmly. “Or am I making you sick?”

The Moments of Bliss satellite lay directly ahead of them; in the center of the breast-shaped landing field the winking pink nipple guided their vehicle to its landing, a mammary invitation beckoning to all. The principle of Yin, out in space, inflated to cosmic proportions.

“It’s a wonder George Walt can perambulate,” Jim said. “Joined at the base of the skull, the way they are. Must be damned awkward.”

“What’s your point?” Sal sounded tense and irritable now.

Jim Briskin said, “No particular point. But you’d think one would have sacrificed the other long ago, for purpose of utility.”

“Have you ever actually seen them?”

“No.” He had never even been to the satellite.

“They’re fond of each other,” Sal Heim said.

The jet-bus began to settle on to the landing field of the satellite; the spin of the satellite provided its constant magnetic flux, sufficient to hold smaller objects to it, and Jim Briskin thought, That’s where we made our mistake. We should never have allowed this place to become attractive -in any sense whatsoever. It was feeble wit, but the best he could manage under the circumstances.

Maybe Pat’s right, he realized. Maybe I—and Sal Heim—will never return from this place. It was not the kind of thought he enjoyed thinking; the Golden Door satellite was not at all the kind of place he wanted to wind up. Ironic that I should be going here now, for the first time, under these circumstances, he said to himself.

The doors of the jet-bus slid back as the bus rolled to a halt.

“Here we are,” Sal Heim said, and got quickly to his feet. “And here we go.” Along with the party volunteers he moved towards the nearest exit. Jim Briskin, after a moment, followed.

At the entrance gate the pretty, dark-haired, unclad attendant on duty smiled a white-tooth smile at them and said, “Your tickets, please.”

“We’re all new here,” Sal Heim said to her, getting out his wallet. “We’ll pay in cash.”

“Are there any girls you wish to visit in particular?” the attendant asked, as she rang the money up on her register.

Jim Briskin said, “A girl named Sparky Rivers.”

“ALL OF YOU?” The attendant blinked, then shrugged her bare shoulders urbanely. “All right, gentlemen. De gustibus non disputandum est. Gate three. Watch your step and don’t jostle, please. She’s in room 395.” She pointed toward gate three and the group moved in that direction.

Ahead, beyond gate three, Jim Briskin saw rows of gilded, shining doors; over some lights glowed and he understood that those were empty at the moment of customers. And, on each door, he saw the curious animated pic of the girl within; the pics called, enticed, whined at them as they approached each in turn, searching for room 395.

“Hi there!”

“Hello, big fellow.”

“Could you hurry? I’m waiting . . .”

“Well, how are you?”

Sal Heim said, “It’s down this way. But you don’t need her, Jim; I can take you to their office.”

Can I trust you? Jim Briskin asked himself silently. “All right,” he said. And hoped it was a wise choice.

“This elevator,” Sal said. Press the button marked C.” He entered the elevator; the rest of the group followed, crowding in after him, as many as could make it. More than half the group remained outside in the corridor. “You follow us,” Sal instructed them. “As soon as you can.”

Jim touched the C button and the elevator door shut soundlessly. “I’m depressed,” he said to Sal. “I don’t know why.”

“It’s this place,” Sal said. “It isn’t your style at all, Jim. Now, if you were a necktie or a flatware or a poriferous vobile salesman, you’d like it. You’d be up here every day, health permitting.”

“I don’t believe so,” Jim said. “No matter what line of work I was in.” It went against everything ethical—and esthetic—in his makeup.

The elevator door slid back.

“Here we are,” Sal said. “This is George Walt’s private office.” He spoke matter of factly. “Hello, George Walt,” he said, and stepped out of the elevator.

The two mutants sat at their big cherrywood desk in their specially constructed wide couch. One of the bodies sagged like a limp sack and one eye had become fused-over and empty, lolling as it focused on nothing.

In a shrill voice the head said, “He’s dying. I think he’s even dead; you know he’s dead.” The active eye fixed malignantly on Tito Cravelli, who stood with his laser rifle, on the far side of the office. In despair, one of the living hands poked at the dangling, inert arm of his companion body. “Say something!” the head screeched. With immense difficulty the living body struggled to its feet; now its silent companion flopped against it and in horror it pushed the burdening lifeless sack away.

A faint spasm of life stirred the dangling sack; it was not quite dead. And, on the face of the uninjured brother, wild hope appeared. At once it tottered grotesquely toward the door.

“Run!” the head bleated, and clumsily groped for escape. “You can make it!” it urged its still-living companion. The four-legged, scrambling joint creature bowled over the surprised volunteers at the door; together they all went down in a floundering heap, the mutant among them, squealing in panic as the injured body buried the other beneath it, struggling to rise.

Jim Briskin, as George Walt lurched upright, dived at them. He caught hold of an arm and hung on.

The arm came off.

He held onto it as George Walt stumbled up to their four feet and out the office door, into the corridor beyond.

Staring down at it, he said, “The thing’s artificial.” He handed it to Sal Heim.

“So it is,” Sal agreed, stonily. Tossing the arm aside he hastily ran after George Walt; Jim accompanied him and together they followed the mutants along the thick-carpeted corridor. The three-armed organism moved badly, crashing into itself as its twin bodies swung first wide apart and then stunningly together. It sprawled, then, and Sal Heim seized the right hand body around the waist.

The entire body came loose, arm and legs and trunk. But without the head. The other body—and single head—managed, incredibly, to get up and continue on.

George Walt was not a mutant at all. It—he—was an ordinarily-constituted individual. Jim Briskin and Sal watched him go, his two legs pumping vigorously, arms swinging.

After a long time Jim said, “Let’s—get out of here.”

“Right.” Nodding in agreement, Sal turned to the party volunteers who had trickled out into the corridor behind them. Tito Cravelli emerged from the office, rifle in hand; he saw the severed one-armed trunk which had been half of the two mutants, glanced up swiftly with perceptive understanding as the remaining portion disappeared from view past a corner of the corridor.

“We’ll never catch them now,” Tito said.

“Him,” Sal Heim corrected bitingly. “I wonder which one of them was synthetic, George or Walt. And why did he do it? I don’t understand.”

Tito said, “A long time ago one must have died.”

They both stared at him.

“Sure,” Tito said calmly. “What happened here today must have happened before. They were mutants, all right, joined from birth, and then the one body perished and the surviving one quickly had this synthetic section built. It couldn’t have gone on alone without the symbiotic arrangement because the brain—” He broke off. “You saw what it did to the surviving one just now; he suffered terribly. Imagine how it must have been the first time, when . . .”

“But he survived it,” Sal pointed out.

“Good for him,” Tito said, without irony. “I’m frankly glad he did; he deserved to.” Kneeling down, he inspected the trunk. “It looks to me as if this is George. I hope he can get it restored. In time.”

He rose, then. “Let’s get upstairs and back to the field; I want to get out of here.” He shivered.

“Then I want a glass of warm, non-fat milk. A big one.” The three of them, with the party volunteers struggling behind, made their way silently back to the elevator. No one stopped them.

The corridor, mercifully, was empty. Without even a pic to leer and cajole at them.

When they arrived back in Chicago, Patricia Heim met them and at once said, “Thank God.” She put her arms around her husband, and he hugged her tight. “What happened? It seemed to take so long, and yet it actually wasn’t long at all; you’ve only been gone an hour.”

“I’ll tell you later,” Sal said shortly. “Right now I just want to take it easy.”

“Maybe I’ll cease advocating shutting the Golden Door satellite down,” Jim said suddenly.

“What?” Sal said, astonished.

“I may have been too hard. Too puritanical. I’d prefer not to take away his livelihood; it seems to me he’s earned it.” He felt numb right now, unable really to think about it. But what had shocked him the most, changed him, had not been the sight of George Walt coming apart into two entities, one artificial, one genuine. It had been Lurton Sands’ disclosure about the mass of maimed bibs.

He had been thinking about this, trying to see a way out. Obviously, if the maimed bibs were to be awakened at all they would have to be last in sequence. And by then perhaps replacement organs would be available in supply from the UN’s organ bank. But there was another possibility, and he had come onto it only just now. George Walt’s corporate existence proved the workability of wholly mechanical organs. And in this Jim Briskin saw hope for Lurton Sands’ victims.

Possibly a deal could be made with George Walt; he—or they—would be left alone if they would reveal the manufacture of their highly sophisticated and successful artificial components. It was, most likely, a West German firm; the cartels were most advanced in such experimentation. But it could of course be engineers under contract to the satellite alone, in permanent residence there.

In any case, four hundred lives represented a great number, worth any effort at saving. Worth any deal, he decided, with George Walt, which could be brought off.

“Let’s get something warm to drink,” Pat said. “I’m freezing.” She started toward the front door of Republican−Liberal party headquarters, key in hand. “We can fix some synthetic non- toxic coffee inside.”

As they stood around the coffee pot waiting for it to heat, Tito said, “Why not let the satellite decline naturally? As emigration begins it can serve a steadily dwindling market. You implied something along those lines in your Chicago speech anyhow.”

“I’ve been up there before,” Sal said, “as you know. And it didn’t kill me. Tito’s been there before, too, and it didn’t warp or kill him.”

“Okay, okay,” Jim said. “If George Walt leaves me alone, I’ll leave them alone. But if they keep after me, or if they won’t make a deal regarding artif-org construction—then it’ll be necessary to do something. In any case the welfare of those four hundred bibs comes first.”

“Coffee’s ready.” Pat said, and began pouring.

Sipping, Sal Heim said, “Tastes good.”

“Yes,” Jim Briskin agreed. In fact the cup of hot coffee, synthetic and non-toxic as it had to be (only low-stratum dorm-housed Cols drank the genuine thing) was exactly what he needed. It made him feel a lot better.

Although the time was dreadfully late at night, Myra Sands had made up her mind to call Art and Rachael Chaffy at their dorm. She had reached a decision regarding their case, and the moment had arrived to tell them.

When the vidphone connection had been made to their public hall booth, Mrs. Sands said, “I’m sorry to bother you so late, Mr. Chaffy.”

“That’s all right,” Art said, sleepily. Obviously, he and his wife had gone to bed. “What is it?”

“I think you should go ahead and have your baby,” Myra said.

“You do? But . . .”

“If you had listened to Jim Briskin’s Chicago speech, you would know why,” Myra said. “There’ll soon be a need for new families; everything has changed. My advice to you and your wife is to apply to Terran Development for permission to emigrate by means of their new system. You might as well be among the first. You deserve to be.”

Bewildered, Art Chaffy said, “Emigrate? You mean they finally found a place? We don’t have to stay here?”

“Buy a homeopape,” Myra said patiently. “Go out now and get it; find a vending machine, read about the speech. It’ll be on the front page. And then start packing your things.” TD will have to accept you, she knew. Because of Jim Briskin’s speech. They’ve been deprived of a choice.

“Gee, thanks, Mrs. Sands,” Art Chaffy mumbled, dazed. “I’ll tell Rachael right away; I’ll wake her up. And—thanks for calling.”

“Good night, Mr. Chaffy,” Myra said. “And good luck.” She hung up, then, satisfied.

Too bad, she thought, that there’s no way I can celebrate. Unfortunately no one else is up this late. Because that’s what this calls for: some kind of a party.

But at least she could go to bed tonight with a clear conscience.

For perhaps the first time in years.

Notes

Philip K.Dick Cantata-140, 1963, (‘F&SF’, July 1964) Later extended to novel ‘Crack in Space’